<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The anchor of faith Vpon which, a Christian may repose in all manner of temptations. Especially in that great and dangerous gulfe of desperation. Wherein so many ouer-whelmed with the weight and burthen of their sinne, and not resisting themselues by the hand of faith, vpon the promises and inuitations of Christ, haue with Caine and Judas most fearefully fallen and shipwrackt themselues, to the vtter confusion both of body and soule for euer.</title>
            <title>Physicke, to cure the most dangerous disease of desperation</title>
            <author>Willymat, William, d. 1615.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1628</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 143 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 56 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A15496</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 25763.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S102508</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99838289</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99838289</idno>
            <idno type="VID">2663</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A15496)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 2663)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1087:07)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The anchor of faith Vpon which, a Christian may repose in all manner of temptations. Especially in that great and dangerous gulfe of desperation. Wherein so many ouer-whelmed with the weight and burthen of their sinne, and not resisting themselues by the hand of faith, vpon the promises and inuitations of Christ, haue with Caine and Judas most fearefully fallen and shipwrackt themselues, to the vtter confusion both of body and soule for euer.</title>
                  <title>Physicke, to cure the most dangerous disease of desperation</title>
                  <author>Willymat, William, d. 1615.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16], 95, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [by M. Flesher] for Robert Wilson, and are to bee sold at his shop at Grayes-Inne new gate in Holbourne,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1628.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>An edition of: Willymat, William.  Physicke, to cure the most dangerous disease of desperation.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Formerly STC 24920.</note>
                  <note>Identified as STC 24920 on UMI microfilm.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Despair --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:2663:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:2663:1"/>
            <p>THE ANCHOR of FAITH.</p>
            <p>Vpon which, A Chriſtian may Repoſe in all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of <hi>Temptations.</hi> Eſpecially in that Great and Dangerous Gulfe of <hi>DESPERATION.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wherein ſo many ouer-whelmed with the weight and Burthen of their <hi>Sinne,</hi> and not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting themſelues <hi>by the Hand of Faith,</hi> vpon the Promiſes and Inuitations of CHRIST, haue with <hi>Caine</hi> and <hi>Judas</hi> moſt fearefully fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len and ſhipwrackt themſelues, to the vtter Confuſion both of <hi>Body</hi> and <hi>Soule</hi> for euer.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>PROV. 18.14.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>The Body will beare his infirmitie; but a Broken and wounded Spirit who can beare.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>St. Auguſt. <hi>in lib. de Vtilitate poenitentiae agendae.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Leaſt wee ſhould increaſe our ſinnes by deſpayring, the gate of Repentance is ſet open vnto vs.</p>
               <p>Leaſt by preſuming, the day of our Death is concealed from vs.</p>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON. Printed for <hi>Robert Wilſon,</hi> and are to bee ſold at his Shop at <hi>Grayes-Inne</hi> new Gate in Holborne. 1628.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:2663:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:2663:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>A PREFACE TO THE Chriſtian Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is a Wonder of the World, a wonder to bee ſeriouſly marked, and diligently conſidered of; and a wonder being ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly marked, and diligently conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of, worthy to bee deepely wayed, and inwardly to bee laid vp in m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> hearts as a thing moſt neceſſary, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable, and auaileable to Chriſtian pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety, and euerlaſting felicity both of ſoule and body,<note place="margin">The thing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> bee <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dred <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſeriou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſidere<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> to ſee and to thinke of it, how carefull, watchfull, diligent, earneſt, and painfull, almoſt all the world euery where is to auoyde, to preuent, to cure, and to remedy, all ſuch troubles, croſſes, griefes, mala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, infirmities, and ſickneſſes as do or may befall the body: And on the other
<pb facs="tcp:2663:3"/> ſide to ſee, or finde ſo few watchfull, carefull, and painefull to auoid, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent, cure or expel the moſt dangerous wounds of the Spirit, the troubles of the conſcience, or deſperation, a miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefe, of all other miſchiefes, moſt needfull to be looked into.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> thing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> bee <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>dred <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſly to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d of.</note>It is a wonder to ſee, and conſider how many there are in the World, which either loath and are aff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aide of bodily ſicknes, or loue &amp; like health, will ſend for and ſeeke, run and ride after bodily Phiſitions, and enquire after the beſt, the moſt expert &amp; moſt skilfull of them, to learne by their di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, and to bee aduiſed by their counſaile (though it coſt their purſe full deare) how to purge and auoide ſuch corrupt humours as may breede (though not preſently bring forth) noyſome diſeaſes, and ſickneſſes: how carefull and how ſcrupulous they are to keepe a temperate order and a dyet in eating and drinking: and how mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate they will be in ſleepe, and all
<pb facs="tcp:2663:3"/> other bodily exerciſes: And on the other ſide, how few there bee in the World that will either abate their ſleepe, forgoe their pleaſures, abridge their dyets, or ſeeke after the ſpirituall Phiſition, or prepare Phiſicke to purge and expell thoſe dangerous &amp; peccant humors, of notorious and hainous ſinnes which in time will both breede &amp; bring forth the moſt deadly diſeaſe of Deſperation, the very Peſte of ſoule and body for euer.</p>
            <p>It is a wonder to ſee,<note place="margin">The <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> thing bee <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dred.</note> how many ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horre, and are affraid of worldly po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerty, and for the auoiding thereof, and for the loue and liking of tranſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory riches, will with great carke and care riſe vp early, and late take their reſt: they will fare hardly, and go clad full barely: they will hazard both bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies and ſoules; they will toyle and teare their fleſh in vnmeaſurable la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours by land and ſea, bee the weather faire, bee it foule, <hi>per mare pauperiem fugientes, per ſaxa, per ignes:</hi> And yet
<pb facs="tcp:2663:4"/> on the other ſide, how few can abide any coſtes charges or paines, to eſcape and remedie ſpirituall decayes, to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoyde pouerty of conſcience, or in time before it be too late, to beware that they be not plunged ere they be aware into the moſt deadly and diue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh gulph of Deſperation; as though ſaluation, and peace of a godly conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, were a matter not worthy the talking of, or labouring for.</p>
            <p>It is a lamentable thing to behold, how many in the world will vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take and attempt any thing,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ing to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> bee it ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſo chargeable &amp; troubleſome, not ſluggiſh nor ſleepie, not careleſſe and ſlothfull, but moſt earneſt and watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full moſt careful and painefull, at euery aſſay, by Prudence and proweſſe, by witte and by warineſſe, by counſaile and by cunning, by learning and by labouring, ambitiouſly to hunt gaine, and gape after honor, and vnfatiga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly ſeeke to attaine fame, and highly account of it to be gazed on, &amp; talked
<pb facs="tcp:2663:4"/> of, with the eyes and tongues of all men. And againe, how few take any care at all, or once endeauour them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues to auoyd ſhame &amp; confuſion in the preſence of the Almighty, to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come glorious in the ſight of GOD and his Angels, and to vſe and exerciſe any of thoſe good meanes and inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments ordained and appointed of God for the increaſe of Faith, Hope, and Charity: and for the weakening and abandoning of all deſperation and diffidence in Gods infinite mercies, and infallible promiſes.</p>
            <p>It is a lamentable thing to marke and conſider how vigilant careful,<note place="margin">The ſe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to bee <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mented</note> and heedfull many of the wiſer, and cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſpecter ſort of men of this world will bee to eſcape, and auoyd all the penalties, paines and puniſhments prouided and ſet downe, for offenders of mortall mens lawes; how painefull they will be in Penall Statutes, &amp; how skilfull in euery branch of the Ciuill Lawes, leaſt they ſhould ignorantly
<pb facs="tcp:2663:5"/> incurre the dangers of impriſonment, of loſſe of landes, forfeytures of their goods or death it ſelfe.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Many haue greater care of mortal mens laws then of Gods lawes.</note>But the mighty God, the only high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Law-giuer, that Lord of Lordes, and King of all Kings, Let him or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deyne, publiſh, and proclaime his Lawes, Statutes, and Ordinances, to be hearkned vnto, obſerued, and kept, and that vnder neuer ſo rigorous and Seuere conditions, puniſhments, and penalties: How few men will ſearch his Booke of Statutes and Lawes? How few are affraid of his, not tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porary, but euerlaſting threatninges and puniſhments, contained in his Lawes? and how few men regard, eſteeme, and thankfully embrace his couenant of reconciliation, ſet forth in his moſt ioyfull, and comfortable Goſpell?</p>
            <p>And yet moſt certaine it is, that all theſe aforeſaid things ſo much to bee wondred at, and ſo greatly to bee la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented for: ſo lightly looked on, ſo
<pb facs="tcp:2663:5"/> ſmally regarded, and ſo little thought on, &amp; many ſuch other of the like fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternity and order of diſorders, &amp; ſins being delighted in, and ſecurely conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued in, without all care or indeauour to forſake them in time, by repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, &amp; true returning to the Lord, doe firſt breed or in gender, and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards bring forth Deſperation; then the which, all the Furies, and Diuells in hell, cannot lightly excogitate nor find out a greater torment or a more intolerable paine, and that becauſe that all other torments, penalties, and paines are but temporall, and purſue men no further then bodily death; but this endeth not with bodily death, but becommeth eternall. Whoſoeuer then he bee, that is once ſurely catcht in this net of deſperation, hee needes no mo accuſers to come againſt him, then his former vnrepented ſinnes, which lye at the doore to arreſt him; his owne heart will giue euidence a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him, and his owne iniquity
<pb facs="tcp:2663:6"/> wil plead him to be guilty, and that to his owne face.</p>
            <p>Vpon conſideration of theſe things I haue now in this treatiſe following, (good Chriſtian Reader) endeuoured my ſelfe to ſet downe, Firſt, a definiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Deſperation; then the grieuouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe thereof: after this, certaine principall cauſes thereof: together with remedies for the ſame: and laſtly a generall preſeruatiue againſt Deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, ariſing of what cauſe ſoeuer: To the intent, that the Children of GOD, falling by ſome occaſions into ſome degrees of it, (for if it rage in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremities, in the opinion of ſome lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Writers, it is an euill incurable, and vnrecouerable) may with the more caſe and quietneſſe bee recouered, and ſaued as it were out of the Diuels clawes; euen out of as great danger as euer were the poore Sheepe that <hi>Dauid</hi> tooke out of the Beares or Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons mouth.<note place="margin">1 Sa, 17.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Accept heereof (gentle Reader)
<pb facs="tcp:2663:6"/> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>h no worſe a minde, then I haue at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>mpted to bee the Writer; and then <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oubt not, but it ſhall either mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r vnto thine heart ſome comforta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Phyſicke, or elſe giue thee occaſion to ſeeke, reade, or collect a better.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Thine in all Chriſtian affection.</hi> W. W.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:2663:7"/>
            <head>The Contents of this Booke entreated of in euery ſeuerall <hi>Page as followeth.</hi>
            </head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>A</hi> Definition of euery thing which is to bee <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>puted or reaſoned of, is neceſſary, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> wherefore.</item>
               <item>The Definition of Deſperation of two ſorts. Page 1</item>
               <item>Two kindes of Deſperation: the one wicked, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> other good and holy. pag. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </item>
               <item>Three thinges eſpecially to be noted in the Treat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of Deſperation. Page <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </item>
               <item>GOD is conſtant and faithfull: and how, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> wherein. Page <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </item>
               <item>The duty of the faithfull towards God, in rega<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> of Gods faithfulnes towards him. Page <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </item>
               <item>The horriblenes of the ſinne of Diffidence, Miſtru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> or Deſperation. Page <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </item>
               <item>When eſpecially the Diuell beginneth to tempt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Deſperation. Page <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </item>
               <item>What kinde of Phiſicke and Surgery the Diue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> practiſeth. Page <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </item>
               <item>The abſurd dealing of ſuch as yeld to Deſperation Page <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </item>
               <item>What great inconueniences they fall into, that yee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to Deſperation. Page <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </item>
               <item>Saint <hi>Bernard</hi> his opinion concerning the haynouſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes of the ſinne of Deſperation. Page <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Scilla</hi> and <hi>Charibdis</hi> is not ſo dangerous as Deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration. Page <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </item>
               <item>The dangers of Deſperation. Page 10 &amp; 11</item>
               <item>Of the degrees by which the Diuell draweth me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> into Deſperation. Page 13</item>
               <item>The Diuell the chiefe cauſe of Deſperation. Page 13</item>
               <item>The forerunners of Deſperation. Page 14</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:2663:7"/>
               <item>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hat the Diuell will obiect to bring vs to deſpera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Page 15</item>
               <item>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>norance the ſecond cauſe of deſperation. Page 16</item>
               <item>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>norance the mother of Deſperation. Page 17</item>
               <item>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eruitude or bondage of ſinne the third cauſe of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eſperation. Page 17</item>
               <item>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he wofull effects of ſins. Page 18</item>
               <item>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he fourth cauſe of Deſperation. Page 18</item>
               <item>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he manifold aduerſaries of mans ſaluation, all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hich the Diuel vſeth as meanes to Deſperation Page 19.</item>
               <item>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he fift cauſe of Deſperation. Page 20, &amp; 21</item>
               <item>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he ſixt cauſe of Deſperation. Page 22</item>
               <item>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ong cuſtome groweth into a ſecond nature. Page 22</item>
               <item>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he firſt preſeruatiue againſt Deſperation. Page 88</item>
               <item>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n example ſhewing that many men put more truſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n mortall man then in God. Page 89</item>
               <item>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nother proofe that many put more truſt in mortall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> man then in God. Page 90</item>
               <item>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he ſecond generall helpe againſt Deſperation. Page 91</item>
               <item>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he third generall helpe againſt Deſperation. Page 92</item>
               <item>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hatſoeuer could be looked for at Gods hands or whatſoeuer man could be charged with, that hath Chriſt performed. Page 93</item>
               <item>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he fourth generall helpe for the auoyding of Deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tion. Page 94</item>
               <item>The fift generall helpe againſt Deſperation. Page 95</item>
               <item>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aint <hi>Paul</hi> and Saint <hi>Iames</hi> their counſell againſt the temptations and aſſaults of Sathan. Page 24</item>
               <item>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> deſcription of the Armour with which Saint <hi>Paul</hi> would haue Chriſtians to reſiſt the Diuell. Page 25</item>
               <item>The firſt kind of Armour to reſiſt the Diuell with. Page 25</item>
               <item>The ſecond kinde of armour werewith the Diuell is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> to be reſiſted. Page 25</item>
               <item>Whereby the Diuel is emboldened to tempt, &amp; wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by
<pb facs="tcp:2663:8"/> on the other ſide he is diſcouraged. Page <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </item>
               <item>The third kind of armour againſt Sathan. Page <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </item>
               <item>The fourth kind of Armour againſt Sathan. Page <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </item>
               <item>What <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aith is. Page <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </item>
               <item>The ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t k<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd of armour to reſiſt the Diuell. Page <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </item>
               <item>The Scriptures do miniſter ſtore of Armour agai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> euery kind of temptation. Page <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </item>
               <item>The ſixt kind of Chriſtian Armour. Page <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </item>
               <item>Remedies againſt igno ance. Page <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </item>
               <item>The danger of wilfull Ignorance. Page <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </item>
               <item>What the Ignorant muſt do. Page <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </item>
               <item>Counſell very neceſſary for the ignorant. Page <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </item>
               <item>What the miniſters of Gods word are. Page <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </item>
               <item>How the Miniſters of Gods word are to bee acco<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted of. Page <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </item>
               <item>Of the great ſeruitude and bondage of ſinnes, and the remedies thereof. Page <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </item>
               <item>Examples tending to the ſtrengthening of our Fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Page <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </item>
               <item>Hope, and Patience againſt Deſperation. Page 39. &amp; 4<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </item>
               <item>Wherefore Chriſt came into this world. Page 41. 42. &amp; 4<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </item>
               <item>What manner of righteouſnes God requireth at o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> hands. Page <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </item>
               <item>Sinne dwelleth euen in the beleeuers, &amp; in the m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> righteous in the world: but yet raigneth not neyth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> can it condemne them, and why, Page 46 &amp; 4<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </item>
               <item>Places of Scripture letting forth Gods great mer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Page 4<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </item>
               <item>A Catalogue or rehearſall of many things, where<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the Diuell craftily tempteth many men to ſin a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Deſperation. Page <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </item>
               <item>How the Diuell tempteth by riches. Page <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </item>
               <item>How the Diuell tempteth by pouerty. Page <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </item>
               <item>How the Diuell tempteth by friends. Page <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:2663:8"/>
               <item>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ow the Diuel tempteth by enemies. Page 52</item>
               <item>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ow the Diuel tempteth by carefulnes. Page 52</item>
               <item>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ow the Diuel tempteth by ſecurity and careleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es. Page 52</item>
               <item>How the Diuell tempteth by ſtrength, by health. a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleneſſe of body, beauty, by honour and dignity, by quicknes of ſpirit and ſharpnes of wit. Page 52. &amp; 53.</item>
               <item>How the Diuel tempteth by Gods word, &amp; how hee wil abuſe wreſt and miſapply Gods word. Page 53. &amp; 54.</item>
               <item>The true vſe of thoſe Scriptures which the Diuell ſeeketh to abuſe, to bring men to Deſperation thereby. Page 55</item>
               <item>The comforts and commodities of the croſſes and aflictions of Gods children. Page 57, &amp; 58.</item>
               <item>Why God ſend<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>th euils to his children, and how he ſendeth comforts in the midſt of euils. Page 59.</item>
               <item>How God loue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h and dealeth with his children. Page 60</item>
               <item>Gods <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>od<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of what ſort they are. Page 61</item>
               <item>What God ſéeketh to worke by dealing hardly with his children. Page 62</item>
               <item>Go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s affection to his children like vnto a kind lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing mothers affection. Page 63, &amp; 64.</item>
               <item>God dealeth with his children as Phiſitions &amp; Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ns do with their Patients. Page 65</item>
               <item>God vſeth ſometimes the ſeruice and miniſtry of Diuels and of wicked men. Page 67</item>
               <item>The wicked are not be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tered by their troubles and aflict ons. Page 67</item>
               <item>Whence it commeth that afflictions and croſſes pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit Gods children. Page 67</item>
               <item>The conceits and opinions of the wicked in their ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſities and troubles. Page 68, &amp; 69</item>
               <item>The ends that the Diuell brings the wicked vnto by their aflictions troubles and croſſes: Page 70</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:2663:9"/>
               <item>Two commodities to bee reaped by the liues, and manner of the deaths of the wicked. Page 71</item>
               <item>The great danger of cuſtom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in ſinne, and of delay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of amendment of life. Page 71, &amp; 72</item>
               <item>A compariſon ſhewing the danger of long cuſtome and w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ltring in ſinne. Page 72 &amp; 73</item>
               <item>Whence repentance and amendment of life are to be had, and how they are to be come by. Page 74</item>
               <item>Many are and may bee deceiued in the manner and time o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> their repentance. Page 75</item>
               <item>A note for ſuch as defer repentance vnto their laſt day. Page 75</item>
               <item>Examples ſhewing that it is dangerous truſting vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the laſt howre. Page 76</item>
               <item>Notable examples of ſodaine and vnprouided death out off holy Scriptures, &amp; other writers Page 76, 77, 78.</item>
               <item>A catalogue or rehearſall of ſundry lets and impedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments which oftentimes fall out when we come to our laſt houre, to hinder and pur by that late repentance which ſo many truſt to at the end of their liues. Page 81 &amp; 82</item>
               <item>The effects of choller in time of extreame ſicknes Page 82</item>
               <item>The manner how the Diuell will buſie himſelfe to hinder repentance, at our laſt pant. Page 38</item>
               <item>The example of <hi>Ioſeph</hi> of <hi>Arimathia</hi> moſt worthy to be imicated. Page 85</item>
               <item>The vſe and cuſtome of the <hi>Egiptians</hi> to bridle euill actions. Page 86</item>
               <item>The notable and imitable example of King <hi>Eze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chias.</hi> Page 86</item>
            </list>
            <trailer>Finis.</trailer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:2663:9"/>
            <head>Of Deſperation.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAPTER. 1</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>The firſt Chapter conteyning the Defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition, and Diuiſion of Deſperation.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>. T. Cicero,</hi> that moſt worthy Father of the <hi>Roman</hi> eloque<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce was of that mind,<note place="margin">A definiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry thing which is to be diſputed or reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned of, is neceſſary and wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore.</note> that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery thinge which was to be reaſoned &amp; diſputed of, ſhould firſt begin at the definition thereof, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o it might briefly be vnderſtood what the ſubſtance of the matter was where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f reaſoning or diſputation was to be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>olden: Of the like opinion and minde <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m I at this preſent, concerning the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>angerous peſte of moſt wicked and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>amnable Deſperation; being the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er which now I haue in hand (through Gods aſſiſtance) to write of.</p>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:2663:10"/>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Definition of Deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration is of two ſorts.</note>The Definition then of Deſperation I finde and read to bee of two ſortes as concerning the words, and yet in ſenſe and ſubſtance of matter little differing one from the other: Whereof the one is, <hi>Deſperatio eſt horribilis mentis &amp; cordis ſeu co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcientiae <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>repidatio ex ſenſu irae di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinae propter peccatum concepta cum metu aeternae damnationis,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The firſt Definition of Deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration.</note> 
                  <hi>ſine vlla ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectatione veniae.</hi> Deſperation is an hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible feare, or trembling of the mind and heart or conſcience, conceiued through a ſence and feeling of Gods wrath for ſin; with a feare of eternal damnation, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out all expectation or hope of pardon or forgiueneſſe thereof.</p>
               <p>The other (which is a far more ancient Definition) is this <hi>Deſperatio eſt malum quo quis diffidit de volu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tate dei,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d Definition of deſpera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> 
                  <hi>aeſtima<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s malitiam ſua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> magnitudine<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> diuinae miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricordiae &amp; bonitatis excedere.</hi> Deſpera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is an euil through which a man mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruſting deſpaireth vtterlie, &amp; is paſt all hope of the good will of God, verily thinking that his naughtines, or ſins, excell the mercies and goodnes of God, according to that ſaying of the firſt deſperat man <hi>Cain: Mine iniquitie is
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:2663:10"/> greater then can be pardoned.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 4.13</note> 
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 4.13</p>
               <p>Thus it being made plaine and eaſie what deſperation is by theſe aforeſaid Definitions, it followeth in the next place, (to procéed after the ſame order that the ſaid <hi>Cicero</hi> vſed) that I ſpeak of diuiſion of Deſperation;<note place="margin">Two kinds of Deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration the one wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther holy.</note> which I like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe finde and read to be of two kinds: the one a wicked kind of Deſperation of Gods promiſes, power, goodnes &amp; mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy towards ſinners, the matter which here I am to entreat of: The other an holy Deſperation of a mans owne po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer, in the obtaining of eternall life, conceiued and wrought by a ſenſe or feeling of a mans owne defects, infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie, &amp; corruptions. Concerning this former kinde of Deſperation, being eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially the marke which I would haue poore ſilly diſtreſſed ſoules to haue a diligent and a watchfull eye vnto, to the intent that both my ſelfe, and my poore brethren, liuing and warring yet with mee in the militant Church of Chriſt here on earth, may be the better fore-warned (for that as they ſay <hi>Tela raeuiſa minus nocent</hi>) of this moſt ſubtil <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd deadly ſtratageme, concerning this
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:2663:11"/> moſt dangerous and fatal aſſaulting en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine, of the Arch-enemy of our ſoules, this deepe diſpayre and diueliſh ſoule-poyſon, I haue thought good by the penning of this ſhort Treatiſe, to put my ſelfe and others in remembrance of theſe three points;<note place="margin">Three thinges eſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pecially to be noted in this Tr atiſe of Deſperati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</note> to wit, firſt of the haynouſneſſe, grieuouſneſſe, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitiouſnes of Deſperation. Secondly, of the cauſes thereof: and thirdly of the remedies.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 2.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>The ſecond Chapter, wherin is deſcribed how hainous, grieuous, hurtfull, and pernitious, the ſinne of Deſperation is.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>IN ſundry and manifold places of ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly Scriptures are we taught, that <hi>Go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> is faithfull,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Cor. 1.9 2. Theſ. 3 3 1 Ioh. 1.9 2 Co. 1.20</note> faithfull in his words, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> true in all his promiſes: <hi>All the promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of God are Yea and amen:</hi> Faithful<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in his mercies, for they neuer fayle <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Faithfull, Iuſt, &amp; True are his waies <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> according to the ſong of the holy An<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gells.<note place="margin">GOD is conſtant &amp; faithfull: &amp; how, and wherein.</note> 
                  <hi>Reu.</hi> 15.3. Yea moreouer, God is carefull for the Faithfull, and hat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:2663:11"/> promiſed to be <hi>their God,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Reu 15.3 2 Cor. 6.18</note> 
                  <hi>and they ſhall be his people.</hi> It is thy duty therfore, O Man! to doe GOD this honour, to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieue without all wauering, doubting, or deſpairing;<note place="margin">The duty of the faith full to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards god in regard of Gods faithfulnes towards him.</note> that GOD hath both Power and Will to doe all thinges that hee promiſeth, and not to permit any ſuch cogitations, thought, or conceite, once to enter into thine heart, as that God ſhould proue himſelfe a lyer; or that it ſhould not come to paſſe, which he hath promiſed. But if thou once ſuffer the diſtruſt and diffidence in Gods pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed mercies (through the multitude of thy ſinnes, and the grieuouſneſſe of thine offences, through the nature of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>inne it ſelfe and the crafty ingeſtion and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uggeſtion of Satan) to take hold of,<note place="margin">The hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riblenes of the ſinne of Diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, Miſtruſt, or Deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration,</note> and poſſeſſe thine heart: O horrible and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rieuous is this laſt ſin of Deſpayring <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hich thou addeſt to thy former ſinnes. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o hainous, ſo hurtfull and pernitious, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s this thy ſin of Diffidence and diſtruſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n Gods mercies to be obtained, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ing to his promiſed word, that I may <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y of thee,<note place="margin">Aug in lib de vtilitate paenitentiae agendae.</note> as <hi>S. Auguſtine</hi> ſaid of <hi>Iudas</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e traytor, <hi>Non tam ſcelus quod eom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>iſiſti quam indulgentiae deſperatio facit
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:2663:12"/> te penitus interire:</hi> Not ſo much the ſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> which thou haſt done, as thy deſpayr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> of forgiueneſſe, hath vtterly caſt the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> away. Surely <hi>Iudas</hi> his deſpayre and diſtruſt (according to S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> his opinion) was a more grieuous ſin, them his treaſon in the betraying of his Mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter.<note place="margin">Ier. ſuper Pſa. 108.</note> Wher-vnto agreeth S. <hi>Iero. Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gis inquit offendit deum Iudas, in ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> quod deſperando ſcipſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſuſpendit, quam in hoc quod d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>u<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> tradidit. Deſperatio e<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nim reddit hominem maledictum, et pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tectione derindignum. Iudas</hi> (ſaith <hi>S. Ie<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rome</hi>) more offended God herein, that in diſpayre he hanged himſelfe, then in tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> hee betrayed his Lord and Maiſter: Fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Deſperation maketh a man accurſed, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> vnworthy Gods protection. And thu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> likewiſe <hi>Cain</hi> his diſpayring in God mercy after his murther committed was a more grieuous ſinne, then th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſhedding of his brother <hi>Abell</hi> hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> blood: For to adde Deſpayre to fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mer ſinnes, is to drawe ſinne afte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſinne as it were with Cart-ropes, t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> heape ſinne vpon ſinne, to fulfill th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> meaſure of iniquitie, and ſo to pu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>chaſe ſwift and moſt certaine damnat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on.
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:2663:12"/> It is indeede the faſhion and olde wont of Sathan,<note place="margin">When eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially the Diuell beginneth to tempt to deſpayre.</note> to perſwade man (when hee hath once committed many haynous ſinnes) after his owne ſinnes, to deſpayre, and ſo to commit the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſinne after the leſſer: which is as if an vnlearned ignorant ond a murthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring Phyſition ſhould cauſe his Patient for the remedring of a little cold taken to drinke the iuyce of Hemlocke which by adding cold to cold, is moſt ſure to bring preſent death; Or as if a man, hauing an Ache in one of his fingers, ſhould cut off the whole hand to take away the Ache of a finger.<note place="margin">Note what kinde of phiſick and ſurgery the Diuell practiſeth.</note> Euen ſuch like Phiſicke and Surgery doth the Diuell practiſe to miniſter vnto lewde and wilfull ſinnors, when hee inticeth and draweth them after many prece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent haynous ſinnes, through deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>payre of finding mercie and forgiue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to ſhorten their liues, by kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling and murthering them-ſelues, by poyſoning, by ſtabbing, by throat-cutting, by drowning, by <hi>Iudas</hi>-like han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging of themſelues; &amp; finally by caſting off all vſe of faith, all vſe of hope, and ſo
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:2663:13"/> quite to deſpayre of Gods mercy: then the which, what can be a more dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous courſe for any man to yeeld vnto? What can be more fooliſh or contrary to all reaſon, if a mans reaſon were not blinded and bewitched that hee could not ſee, nor perceiue, nor conſider well of it, then whiles a man is afraid of water, preſently to caſt her ſelfe head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long into it,<note place="margin">The ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurd de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings of ſuch as ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily yeeld to deſpera<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion.</note> and ſo ſeeingly and wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tingly to drowne himſelfe? or then whiles a man is afraid of fire, preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to runne into it and to diſpatch him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe therein? Or whiles a man is afraid of hell fire, out of hand moſt deſperate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to plunge himſelfe into the daungers thereof?</p>
               <p>And yet ſuch as theſe are the perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, and temptations of the Diuell, to a man whoſe barking conſcience conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually pangeth and plagueth him for his ſinnes.</p>
               <p>Such as theſe are the fruites of the moſt monſtrous ſinne of diſpayring of Gods mercy and grace.</p>
               <p>May not he be accounted worſe then madd,<note n="*" place="margin">Marke this O man, leaſt thou yeeld to Deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thou be awa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e what great inco<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences thou yeeldeſt vnto.</note> that is ſo foreward and ready to yéeld vnto, and to follow after the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uells
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:2663:13"/> whiſtle, alluring and entiſing vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to deſperation, ſeeing it is no meanes to diminiſh, but to encreaſe ſinne, and the rewards of ſinne, ſeeing that it is no reliefe, but an euerlaſting burthen and griefe of the ſoule: ſeeing that it is not a deliuery of the ſoule, but a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine deſtruction of the ſoule: ſeeing it is not a redemption, but an vndoub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted condemnation of ſoule and body for euer.</p>
               <p>And finally, ſeeing that it changeth temporall griefe into eternall griefe, and the panges of conſcience, into the paines of hell for euer. And thus is verified that ſaying of <hi>S. Bernard, Deſperatio auget peccatum,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Saint <hi>Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard</hi> his opinion concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peration.</note> 
                  <hi>Deſperatio maior eſt omnibus peccatis, Deſparatio peior eſt omni pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cato,</hi> Deſperation encreaſeth ſin: Deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peration is greater then al other ſinnes, Deſperation is worſe then all other ſinnes.</p>
               <p>This is a thouſand times worſe then the dangerous rocke Scilla, againſt which ſo many poore Marriners haue daſhed their ſhippes,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Scilla</hi> and <hi>Charybdis</hi> not ſo dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous as deſperati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</note> to the great loſſe both of Shippes, goodes and liues: or then that no leſſe dangerous gulfe Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rybdis,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:2663:14"/> which haue deuoured vp ſo many paſſengers: For at this vnfortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate and deadly rocke of Deſperation, many thouſan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s of poore ſoules ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged with the burthen of their ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities, and turmoyled in their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences with the waues of fearefull thoughts, and troubleſome conceites by the bluſtring blaſtes and ſurgie ſtormes of Gods vengeance threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned againſt ſinners, both haue and day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly doe make dangerous and fearefull ſhip-wracke. This is a worſe dungeon for both ſoules and bodies of poore deſperate ſinners: then was the Denne of Lyons, into the which the Rulers, Officers,<note place="margin">Dan. 6.17</note> and Gouernours of King <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius</hi> cauſed <hi>Daniell</hi> to be caſt, and clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed vppe:<note place="margin">Dan 3.19</note> Yea, and this is ſeauen times worſe then the ſeauen times heated bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Ouen or Furnace, into the which that proud Idolatrous King <hi>Nabuchad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nezzer</hi> commanded <hi>Sidrach, Miſach,</hi> and <hi>Abednago,</hi> the true ſeruants and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhippers of the onely true and euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuing God, to be caſt in. This is that incurable, remedileſſe, and deſperate ſore, wound and maladie, which the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:2663:14"/> Prophets of God <hi>Ieremy</hi> and <hi>Micheas,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ier. 3. Mic. 1.</note> in their dayes complained of among their people. This is that great ſtop &amp; let, that hindereth and reſiſteth Gods holy grace from flowing and entring into the ſoules of ſinfull men. This is the Axe that heweth and choppeth a ſunder the chaines wherewith God in his great mercy, and mercifull kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, would drawe the hearts of ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners vnto himſelfe by Repentance; whereof ſpeaketh the Prophet <hi>Ozeas.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Oze. 11.</note> 
                  <hi>Truſt in the Lord, and doe good,</hi> ſaith the holy Ghoſt by the Prophet <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 37.3</note> where hee placeth and ſetteth <hi>Truſt in GOD</hi> in the firſt place, and <hi>doing good</hi> in the ſecond: <hi>truſting in GOD,</hi> goeth before as the Miſtris, and <hi>doing good</hi> followeth &amp; attendeth on as the Hand-maide: For as it is ſaid <hi>Spes alit agricolas,</hi> were it not for Hope the Huſbandmans heart would burſt; Hope nouriſheth his heart: Euen ſo Deſpayre and diffidence, or diſtruſt in GOD, is a Step-mother to well do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and draweth backe from doing good; according to the ſaying of a learned Writer vpon the ſaid 37. Pſal.
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:2663:15"/> 
                  <hi>Deſperatio &amp; diffidentia abſtrahit ab omni ſtudio honi nam cogitat omnia fieri fruſtra:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Muſculus in Pſ. <hi>37.3</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>ita namque ex ſpe et fiducia pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manant mortaliu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> conatus, vt ex ipſis co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natibus ſatis liqucat quid quiſque ſperat.</hi> Deſperation and Miſtruſt draweth back from all deſire of well doing,<note place="margin">Deſparati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth men back from all wel do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and why.</note> for it thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth all to be but loſt labour: for ſo doe all mens labours and endeauours flowe and ſpring from Hope and truſt, that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery mans doings doe plainly teſtifie what he hopeth or truſteth for.</p>
               <p>And now let this ſuffice briefely to giue a taſte how great and grieuous, hurtfull and pernitious this ſinne of Deſperation is.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 3.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>The third Chapter conteining the chie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt and moſt principall cauſes of Deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peration.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>THat memorable and notable ſaying of <hi>S. Gregory</hi> in one of his Homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies, moueth mee to thinke, and here to commit it to writing, that one cauſe of Deſperation, and not the leaſt, but
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:2663:15"/> rather the primary and principall cauſe of all other ariſeth from the ſubtile, cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and coſoning counſell, inducement, perſwaſion, and allurement of the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell: for ſaith <hi>S. Gregory,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Greg. in quadam Hom.</note> 
                  <hi>Quum in graui peccato miſer homo labitur: ſua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>det ei diabolus ne peniteat, ne co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fiteatur peccatum leue et modicum in corde affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mat, miſericordiam praedicat, longum ſpaciu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vitae promittit, permanere in pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cato ſuggerit, vt ſic in contemptum dei, &amp; d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſperationem ſui inducat &amp; pereat:</hi> When wretched man ſlippeth into ſome grieuous ſinne, the Diuells councell is, that he repent not at al for it, that he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe it not: hee tells him in his heart,<note place="margin">The de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees by which the Diuell draweth men on in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to deſpera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> that it is but a light and ſmall offence: hee ſaies God is full of mercie, hee pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſeth him long life, he ſuggeſteth vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him to lie ſtill in ſinne, that by theſe meanes hee may bring him at laſt into contempt of God, and into vtter Deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peration, and ſo hee may become a caſt-away for euer. Here doth <hi>S. Gregory</hi> in moſt manifeſt and plaine words deſcribe and decipher the Diuell himſelfe to bee the author and ſo conſequently the cheefeſt cauſer, and cauſe, of this horri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:2663:16"/> ſoule murthering Deſperation; and here alſo doth he ſet down by what ſteppes and degrees hee brings and leades a poore careleſſe wretched man into deſpayre.</p>
               <p>Now conſider this moreouer, that if <hi>Satan</hi> that arch-enemy of mans wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare,<note place="margin">Iob. 1.</note> durſt very boldly and ſawcely without any bidding, preſume to thruſt himſelfe into Gods preſence amongſt his holy Angells; if hee durſt ſo ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telly and cunningly, diſſemblingly and lyinglie, aſſayle and aſſault our firſt Parents <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eue,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 3.</note> being yet in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocents, vnſtained, and pure from all ſin: Nay more then all this, if he durſt approach and with diuers temptations aſſault and allure <hi>Chriſt Ieſus</hi> himſelfe,<note place="margin">Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 4.3.</note> both God and Man; and yet Man frée from any ſpot or blemiſh of ſinne en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deuoring himſelfe to the vttermoſt of his ſkill and power if it had beene poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, to haue brought him, and wrought him to his owne wicked will: Alaſſe, is it any maruele then if he doe as dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently and buſily beſtirre himſelfe with his manifould wiles, and guiles, to aſſaile vs weake, poore, and miſerable
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:2663:16"/> ſinners? Who (without the dayly and howerly ſtrengthning of Gods holy ſpirit) are of our ſelues prompt, apt and ready,<note place="margin">The fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runners of deſperatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> except we looke to our ſelues in time.</note> euery hower to decline and fall away from God, and to fall vnto Idolatry, Blaſphemy, Periury, Murther, Whoredome, Theft, Pride, Diſobedience, and what not; wherin, after wee be once plunged ouer head and eares, and ouer runne with thee guilt of many ſinnes, then will <hi>Sathan</hi> lay about him, and apply his buſines like a moſt valiant Champion, to catch vs in the moſt dangerous ſnare of all other, euen deepe Deſpayre: He will challenge our ſoules by the ſeuere iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice of GOD, let vs ſay againſt him whatſoeuer we can, and argue againſt him as long as wee will, yet will hee inſult, reioyce, and reply ſaying: Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Gods mercies nor Chriſts merits, can any thing help, but thou muſt needs be damned,<note place="margin">What the Diuell wil obiect a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt vs to bring vs to deſpaire</note> ſo lightly heretofore haſt thou eſteemed God, and his precepts; ſo ſmally haſt thou regarded <hi>Chriſt Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus</hi> and his merits, or rather ſo willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, wittingly, and ſeeingly haſt thou vilipended, and contemned them;
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:2663:17"/> and ſo obſtinately, careleſly, and deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rately, troden them vnder-foote, that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen as thou hitherto haſt made noe reckoning of God, and haſt not opened the doore of thy heart to receiue him, and giue him entertainment when heeſtood without and knocked to bee letten in there; ſo now God will requite thee, with <hi>Legetalionis,</hi> with like for like: hee will make no reckoning of thee, hée will not open his eares vnto thee when thou cryeſt vnto him, hee will not let thee haue though thou aske, hee will not let thee finde though thou ſeeke, hée will not open vnto thee though thou knocke. Behold now art thou toſſed like waues of the Sea, thy Faith waue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth betwéene Hope and Dread, and therefore canſt thou receiue nothing at the Lords hands: with theſe and infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite ſuch like diſputations, will <hi>Sathan</hi> ſet vpon, and vexe the very elect of God, to bring them (if it were poſſible) to deſperation. And if the elect ſhall bee thus fifted, (as <hi>Peter</hi> was) in what caſe then ſhall the wicked and reprobate bee?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:2663:17"/>
               <head>CHAP. 4.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond cauſe of deſpera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note>THe ſecond cauſe of Deſperation, is ignorance of God, &amp; want of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the will of God, vnto mankind reuealed by his holy word:<note place="margin">Mat. 22.</note> for as igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of the ſcriptures, as it was pronou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced by the mouth of <hi>Chriſt Ieſus</hi> himſelfe ſpeaking againſt the <hi>Saduces,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Kin. 17.26. Pſ. 23.10.11. Pr. 28.29 30.31. Eſa. 1.34. Hoſ. 4.7. Eph. 4.18</note> concerning the reſurrection of the dead, was the cauſe of that their ſo great error; Euen likewiſe the ignorance of God, is often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times the occaſion &amp; cauſe of Gods hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uie diſpleaſure; and ſo of diuers &amp; ſundry inconueniences and miſchiefes:<note place="margin">Ber ſuper Cant.</note> and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſt the reſt, it is alſo a cauſe of this curſed Deſperation, as writeth S. <hi>Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard: Vtraque cognitio, dei ſcilicet &amp; tui tibi neceſſaria eſt ad ſalute<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, quia de igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tia tui venit ſuperbia, ac de dei ignora<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia venit deſperatio.</hi> The knowledg both of God, &amp; of thy ſelfe are neceſſary vnto ſaluation, becauſe out of the ignorance of thy ſelfe, ariſeth pride;<note place="margin">Ignorance the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of deſperati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</note> &amp; likewiſe out of the ignorance of God, commeth Deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peration. Out of this ignorance of God, muſt Deſperation needs ariſe: for how can it otherwiſe be, but that hee that is
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:2663:18"/> altogither without any knowledge of God, muſt deſpayre to receiue any good thing of him? for as no man can take pleaſure nor any profit by hid and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowne Treaſure: ſo no man can looke for grace, mercy, and forgiueneſſe of ſinnes, or any other benefit or good gift at his hands, of whom he is vtterly ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant, and of whom he hath no know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 5.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The third cauſe of deſperati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</note>THe third cauſe of Deſperation is the great ſeruitude or bondage or ſinne: with which whoſoeuer is clogged, hee becommeth thereby the ſeruant of ſinne: <hi>Iohn</hi> 8.34. And the wofull and hurtfull effects of ſinnes, are the procurements of Gods curſes and plagues vpon bodyes,<note place="margin">The woful &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>urtfull effects of ſinne.</note> ſoules, lands, children, ſtocke, croppe, and euery thing elſe that a man hath, or goeth about at home or abroade, in town or in field, in Citty or in Contry, by land or by water. <hi>Deu.</hi> 28. <hi>Leu.</hi> 26. Sin har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deneth the heart. <hi>Heb.</hi> 3.13. It fighteth againſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſoule. 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.11. It gnaweth &amp; tormenteth the conſcience. 1. <hi>Sa.</hi> 25.31.
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:2663:18"/> And bringeth men into the moſt dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable gulfe of Deſperation, wherein multitudes of Worldlinges, Matcheuil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lians, Epicures, &amp; impious Atheiſts are dayly implunged, and irreuocably drow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned for euer.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 6</head>
               <p>THe Fourth cauſe of Deſperation do many gather to themſelues vpon the wordes of <hi>Chriſt</hi> in <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.13.<note place="margin">The fourth cauſe of Deſperati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</note> 
                  <hi>Strait is the gate, &amp; narrow is the way that lead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth vnto life, &amp; few there be that find it.</hi> And againe out of <hi>Mat.</hi> 20.16. <hi>Many are called, but few are choſen.</hi> And againe out of <hi>Luk.</hi> 13.24. <hi>Striue to enter in at the ſtraite gate, for many, I ſay vnto you, will ſeeke to enter in &amp; ſhal not be able:</hi> All which places doe plainly teach; that few ſhall be ſaued; for in bidding to ſtriue to enter in, <hi>Chriſt</hi> giueth vs to vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it is no eaſie matter, but a mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that requireth great ſtrife, paines, and earneſt diligence againſt the World, the Fleſh, and the Diuell.</p>
               <p>Vpon theſe conſiderations,<note place="margin">The feare and doubt of many.</note> many be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin to feare and to tremble, to ſtagger,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:2663:19"/> and no doubt, whether they may thinke themſelues to be in the number of thoſe few that ſhall be ſaued yea or no; and ſo are drawne into diſpayre, whiles that they finde this preſent euil world againſt them with all the baytes, ſnares, nettes, and lets, pleaſures, and profits thereof to catch them,<note place="margin">The great and mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>es of mans ſalua<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion: all which the diuel vſeth as meanes to Deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration.</note> fetter them, and intangle them, whiles they finde their own fleſh, their owne corrupted nature againſt them; their reaſon poyſoned, their wils and affections blinded, their naturall wiſdome, concupiſcences, and luſts, mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtring ſtrength to <hi>Satans</hi> temptations, taking part againſt them daily and how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erly ready to betray them into his hands, whiles that they ſee and perceiue euen legions of Diuells, euen all the Diuells in hell againſt them, with all their craf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty heades, maruailous ſtrength, infinite wiles, cunning deuiſes, déep ſlights, and tryed temptations, lying in ambuſh a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt their poore ſoules; &amp; who ſéeth not y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thouſands are caried headlong to deſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uction through the temptations of either the world, the fleſh, or y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> diuell? And thus are we poore wretches in a moſt pittiful caſe aſſaulted and betraied on euery ſide.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:2663:19"/>
               <head>CHAP. 7</head>
               <p>THe fift cauſe of Deſperation ariſeth from the manifold croſſes &amp; afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of this preſent life,:<note place="margin">The fifth cauſe of deſperati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</note> for from hence it is that ſome men being daily feretted, followed on, &amp; euen almoſt preſſed down with temporall afflictions and troubles,<note place="margin">Sundry kinds of croſſes and afflictions.</note> as penury, pouerty, hunger, nakednes, ſicknes of body, troubles of mind, vnqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>et ſuggeſtions of the fleſh, temptations of the Diuel perſecutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, impriſonments, loſſe of friends, loſſe of goods, loſſe of good name and fame, a wicked, crooked, &amp; fro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward mate in matrimony, diſobedient &amp; vntoward children, vnkind &amp; vnthank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full friends, vnderſerued malice, enuy, &amp; hatred of froward neighbours, &amp; many other ſuch like croſſes, as daily in one ſort or other befal men: When they once feele themſelues touched and tryed here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with,<note place="margin">Ier. 20.</note> anon they take occaſion hereby to cry out, and lementably to houle, and curſe the day wherein they were borne,<note place="margin">Ier. 15.</note> to call that an vnhappy houre wherein their mothers brought them forth,<note place="margin">Iob. 3.</note> to wiſh they had dyed in their birth, &amp; that they had periſhed ſo ſoone as they came
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:2663:20"/> out of their mothers wombe; that ſome hill might fall vpon them &amp; ouerwhelme them that ſo they might ſhortly bee rid out of their paines: Yea they will not be perſwaded that theſe thinges are ſent of God (for the moſt part) to ſuch as he lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth, but rather to ſuch as he hateth; and that neuer a louing father wil handle his children ſo as they are handled. Now the Diuell moſt ſubtilly lying in wayte for his aduantoge, taketh hold on this their weakeneſſe, and ſtriueth by little &amp; little by ſuch occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s as theſe to worke vtter deſperation in them; and by theſe meanes oftentimes forceth ſome to ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daine, wretched, and deſperate ends.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 8</head>
               <p>THe ſixt cauſe of Deſperation is long cuſtome of ſin,<note place="margin">The ſixt cauſe of Deſperati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</note> whereby a man yeel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth and ſubmitteth himſelfe as an obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient &amp; ready bon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>-ſlaue to the Diuell, little reſpecting if not vtterly contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning both God and his word, whoſe dull conſcience through giuing himſelfe ouer to impurity &amp; filthines of life, is waxed hard in iniquity, and corrupt waies, and
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:2663:20"/> as it were burned with a hot iron, ſo that he is now paſt all ſenſe &amp; féeling of ſinn,<note place="margin">Long cuſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ome grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth into a ſecond na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</note> &amp; this long coſtome groweth as it were into a ſecond nature (in proceſſe of time) which to expell is a matter of great dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulty. This is it which the Prophet <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rim.</hi> meant, where he affirmed that it is as hard a thing for ſuch to doe any good that haue bin continually inured with doeing of euil, as it is to waſh a Blacka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moore or Aethiopian skinne white: or to chang the ſpots of a Leopard: And therefore according to our Engliſh a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage, as that which is bred in the bone, will neuer lightly out of the fleſh: ſo an old wont or cuſtome of any vice, be it of lying, ſwearing, gaming, drinking, whooring, or any other ſuch like, will ſeldome or neuer be remedied; whereby it oftentimes commeth to paſſe, that in the end y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Diuel by this meanes hauing laid a foundation, ſo fitting his purpoſe to worke on, bringeth his old cuſtomers to diſpaire.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:2663:21"/>
               <head>CHAP. 1.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>The firſt Chapter concerning the Reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies againſt the temptations &amp; aſſaults of Satan, being the firſt ſpeciall cauſe of Deſperation, before intreated of in Ch. 3</p>
               </argument>
               <p>TO méete with the dangerous and manifould temptations of <hi>Satan,</hi> that great enemy of mankind, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with hee continually after other ſinnes firſt committed, laboureth to bring vs into the deepe gulph of deſperation; It ſhall not be amiſſe, nay rather it ſhall be our beſt courſe and remedie, to learne &amp; practiſe that moſt ſure, ſafe, and excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent counſaile, which the holy ghoſt gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth by thoſe two worthy Apoſtles of our Sauiour Chriſt,<note place="margin">Eph: 6. Iam. 4. Saint <hi>Paul</hi> &amp; S. <hi>Iam s</hi> their coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel againſt the temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ns &amp; aſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ults of Sath n.</note> 
                  <hi>S. Paul</hi> and <hi>S. Iames;</hi> wherof <hi>S. Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>Put on the whole ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour of God, that ye may be able to ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d againſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> aſſaults of the Diuel &amp; S. Iam.</hi> ſaith, <hi>Reſiſt the Diuell &amp; he will flie from you:</hi> that is to ſay, we muſt ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iue againſt all vnlawful &amp; forbidden luſts by which hee eggeth, draweth, and haleth men from ſinne to ſinne, from bad to worſe, and finally to deſperation, the worſt of all ſins.</p>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:2663:21"/>
               <p>Had <hi>Cain</hi> thus reſiſted the Diuell, hee had neuer bene ſo far drawn (as he was) from faithleſſe hypocriſie, to enuy; from enuy to murther. and from murther to Deſperation. Had <hi>Iudas</hi> the traytor thus reſiſted the Diuel when he by his intiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment firſt yeelded to couetouſneſſe, and ſo for a little filthy lucre to betray his moſt louing, gentle, and kinde Lord &amp; Maiſter, he had not from thoſe ſins one in the neck of another finally fallen in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to deſpayre, wherein he became his own hang man to the euerlaſting teſtimony of his owne damnation.</p>
               <p>Full worthy therefore, and very néed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full in this caſe is <hi>S. Iames</hi> his counſaile, <hi>Reſiſt the Diuell &amp;c.</hi> yea and that in the beginning.<note place="margin">A diſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the manner of armour with which Saint Paul would haue Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians to reſiſt the Diuell.</note>
               </p>
               <p>And <hi>S. Paul</hi> goeth further on with the like good counſaile, and ſetteth downe very plainely with what manner of Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour he would haue Chriſtians to buc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kle and furniſh themſelues with, that ſo they may be found the more ready and able to encounter their generall enemies temptations: As firſt with <hi>Verity,</hi> or <hi>Truth,</hi> which is the arming of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues with true and ſincere knowledge
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:2663:22"/> of God <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.1.<note place="margin">The firſt kind of Armour to reſiſt the Diuell with.</note> In the true ſeruice of God with out hypocriſie, in <hi>Spirit and truth. Ioſua</hi> 24.14. <hi>Iohn</hi> 4.24. 3. <hi>Kin.</hi> 2.4 And likewiſe with vprighr true ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king &amp; dealing with our neighbours in word and deed <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.25. <hi>Ex.</hi> 23.1.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d kinde of Armour wherwith the Diuell is to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted.</note>Secondly with the <hi>Breſt-plate of righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſnes:</hi> that is, with the earneſt appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng and endeauouring of our ſelues to all vertue and godlines in our liues and conuerſations: Where note, that the Apoſtle hauing placed <hi>Verity, Truth,</hi> or true knowledge of God, in the firſt place: in very fit &amp; good ranck &amp; order he placed this <hi>Righteouſnes;</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> is to ſay practiſe of true knowledge in holines of life in the ſecond place; as a godly father herevpon hath very well obſerued in theſe words: <hi>Vera dei cognitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e &amp; animi ſinceritate, &amp; puritate pr mu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> deinde pia et ſancta vita ornari debe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t Chriſtiani mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites:</hi> Chriſtian Souldiars ought firſt to haue their hearts &amp; minds decked &amp; fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed with true knowledge of God, with true ſincerity &amp; purity of mind; &amp; ſecondly, with Godly &amp; holy life anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable to their true knowledge. Hereby all ſlighty, cunning, &amp; forcible entries
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:2663:22"/> vnto Satans engines and ſubtile ſnares ſhalbe debarred and ſhut vp: hereby all the paſſages of our thoughts and imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations ſhal be preuented and taken vp,<note place="margin">Whereby the Diuell is embol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dened to tempt: and Whereby on the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſide he is diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged, &amp; reſiſted</note> that he ſhall not ſo eaſily find any breach or weake place to inuade. For as on the one ſide, by looſeneſſe &amp; licentiouſneſſe of the fleſh, by lewdneſſe of our liues, by our iniquity and vngodlines, the Diuell is animated, fleſhed, and emboldened, dayly to tempt and aſſault vs: for he ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the corruption of our nature a for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardneſſe to wickednes, he bloweth the bellowes and kindleth the flame of our bad inclination; he ſtirreth vs vp, &amp; pricketh vs forward, till after the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping vp of one ſinne after another, at the length he caſteth vs downe headlong in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bottomleſſe pit of Deſperation: So on the other ſide by this Armour of righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe, ſincerity and integrity to an holy life is the Diuell withſtood and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted, and we become the more able to ſtand faſt in the day of our temptation: So that it is not without iuſt cauſe, that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Apoſtle compareth this <hi>Righteouſnes</hi> the ſecond kind of ſpiritual Armour, vnto a corporall <hi>Braeſt-plate;</hi> for that like as
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:2663:23"/> a Breſt-plate ſaueth and fenceth the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall parts of man,<note place="margin">The good fruites of vprighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes, &amp; holines of life.</note> as his heart, liuer, &amp; entrailes; which once being ſtricken and pierced mans life is loſt: ſo doth vpright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and holines of life, preſerue the heart and conſcience of man free &amp; ſafe from the inuaſion &amp; confuſion wrought by Satan from the fierie darts of infide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie, hardnes of conſcience, coldneſſe in religion, wickednes of life, corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in conuerſation, &amp; finally from Deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, the very vp-ſhot of al miſchiefs.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The third kinde of Armour for a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than.</note>Thirdly, muſt we arme &amp; furniſh our ſelues to reſiſt <hi>Satan</hi> the Diuell, with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
                  <hi>Goſpell of peace,</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> is, our hearts muſt be throughly acquainted, &amp; fully fraugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with the knowledge of that glad ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings of great ioy, which the Angells of the Lord brought at the birth of <hi>Chriſt;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">L. 2.10.</note> that tydinges of great ioy, which muſt be vnto all nations, with that moſt comfortable &amp; ioyfull embaſſage of the Reconciliation of man with God, which may ful w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l be called y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
                  <hi>Goſpel of peace</hi> for that it onely maketh the Conſcience of man quiet, &amp; at peace with God and it ſelfe: then the which, what one thing in all the world, can ſet a man more frée
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:2663:23"/> from all Deſperation?<note place="margin">The fourth Armour. 1. Cor. 16 13.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Fourthly, with <hi>Faith in Ieſus Chriſt;</hi> wherewith the ſame <hi>S. Paul</hi> arming men againſt ſpirituall aſſaults by <hi>Sathan</hi> and his miniſters, and preparing them to the ſpirituall battaile agaiaſt the Diuell and his members, encourageth them not to ſhrinke, but to cleaue faſt to this Faith, whereby we may reſiſt and beat backe our ſpirituall enemie.</p>
               <p>And likewiſe <hi>S. Peter</hi> inſtructing vs to prepare and make oure ſelues ſtrong, to encounter with the common enemy the Diuell, teacheth vs to reſiſt him by faith eſpecially: <hi>Be ſober</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>and watch,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Pet. 5.8</note> 
                  <hi>for your aduerſary the Diuell, goeth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout ſeeking whom hee may deuoure, whom reſiſt ſtedfaſt in faith.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For this cauſe <hi>Saint Baſil</hi> vpon the 32. Pſalme ſaith,<note place="margin">Baſilius in Pſal. 32.</note> 
                  <hi>What man is able to make war with the Diuel, vnles he flee for help to the Captain of the Hoaſt through faith in him, to wound and thruſt through his enemy?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And likewiſe <hi>S. Auguſtine</hi> accounted this faith to be ſo powerfull,<note place="margin">Aug. lib. 3 Cap 20. de lib. arbitri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>o.</note> 
                  <hi>that it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſteth, vanquiſheth and ouer-commeth the Diuell.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:2663:24"/>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">What faith is</note>And this true Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Faith which is of ſuch power as aforeſaid, is a ſure truſt in the mercy of God y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Father through y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> merits of <hi>Chriſt Ieſus,</hi> when we do per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade our ſelues moſt certainly of the pardon of our ſins through <hi>Chriſts</hi> righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſnes; and of eternall ſaluation by his paſſion, heereby obtaining peace in our conſciences w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> God, &amp; reſt, &amp; walke in obedience to his will &amp; commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments by his word vnto vs reuealed. Of this kind of faith is entreated in <hi>Abac.</hi> 2.4. <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.38 <hi>Rom.</hi> 51. <hi>Ephe.</hi> 2.8.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The fift kind of Armour</note>The fift kind of Armor to reſiſt the Diuell with whereof S. <hi>Paul</hi> in the ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talogue of a Chriſtian Souldiars armor maketh reherſal, is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
                  <hi>word of God:</hi> this is the Sword of the ſpirit, whereby the ſuggeſtions and wicked temptations of <hi>Sathan,</hi> are beaten backe, propelled, &amp; kept off, euen as a man kéepeth backe his enemy at the poynt of his Sword.</p>
               <p>With this kinde of Armour did our chiefe captaine <hi>Chriſt Ieſus</hi> in his man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood here on earth, reſiſt and put backe al the Diuell his ſubtle and faulſe temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, anſwering euery one of them with <hi>Scriptu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eſt,</hi> It is written: whence
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:2663:24"/> we may learne by the like meanes,<note place="margin">Chriſt him ſelfe an example how to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uels temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations.</note> after his moſt excellent example to combate with the Diuell, and to giue him the foyle, whenſoeuer by him, or any his wicked inſtruments, we ſhall be temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to this Deſperation, or any other ſinns whatſoeuer.</p>
               <p>If we be tempted to ſweare and blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheme the holy name of God, it is to be reſiſted with <hi>Sciptum eſt,</hi> It is written, <hi>Thou ſhalt not take the name of the Lord thy God in vaine.</hi> If to pollute and break y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lords Sabboth day through ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther labouring about our pleaſures or profits, anſwer, It is written, <hi>Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber that thou kepe holy &amp;c.</hi> If to mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, &amp; ſhedding of blood, by any forbidde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> way or means, or vpon any vnlawfull occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whatſoeuer; anſwere, It is writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, <hi>Thou ſhalt doe no murther.</hi> If to ſteale and purloyne by any vnlawfull means, directly or indirectly; anſwere, it is written, <hi>Thou ſhalt not ſteale</hi> If we be tempted to vſury,<note place="margin">Exo. 22.25. Deu 23.19. Le. 25.39 Pſal. 15.5.</note> let vs drawe out y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Sword of the Spirit, <hi>Thou ſhalt not giue to Vſury vnto thy brother, Vſury of mony, Vſury of meat or of any other thing.</hi> If he moue vs to deceipt &amp; frau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulent
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:2663:25"/> dealing,<note place="margin">1 Theſ. 4.5. Leu 25.14</note> let vs reſiſt him w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>, It is written, <hi>Let no man oppreſs or deceaue his brother in bargaining, for the Lord is a Iudge in ſuch things.</hi> If we be ſollicited to diſloyalty, &amp; diſobedience to Princes, let vs ſtriue againſt that, with, It is written,<note place="margin">Rom. 13.1 2, 3,</note> 
                  <hi>Let euery ſoule be ſubiect to the higher powers &amp;c.</hi> Finally to be ſhort to what kind of ſin, miſchiefe, or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conuenience ſo euer any of vs ſhall hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen to be drawn,<note place="margin">The Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures doe miniſter ſtore of ſwords a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry kinde of temptation</note> inticed, or inueigled, let vs ſearch the Scriptures, &amp; we ſhal ſoone finde ſtore of ſwordes, of one kind or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to anſwer, foyle, and recoyle, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer this mortal enemy of ours can vſe or obiect againſt vs, here is armour e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to finde him occupied with.</p>
               <p>The ſixt kinde of ſpirituall Armour, and heauenly furniture, wherewith <hi>S. Paul,</hi> or rather the holy Ghoſt by <hi>Saint Paul,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The ſixt kinde of Chriſtian Armour.</note> would haue vs complet and furni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed againſt all the dangerous combats, conflicts, and wicked ſuggeſtions of this wicked and damned ſpirit, thereby to auoid, repell, &amp; vanquiſh him vtterly is deuout, hearty, zealous &amp; Godly prayer. Ouer &amp; beſides <hi>S. Paul</hi> his inſtruction, and moſt needfull exhortation, in this
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:2663:25"/> caſe his &amp; our Lord, Maiſter, and Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our <hi>Chriſt Ieſus,</hi> hath commended vnto vs this kind of weapon, when he taught to pray w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> this petition. <hi>And lead vs not into temptation but deliuer vs from euill.</hi> Let vs then apply this Armor, this kind of propulſatiue weapon, and feruentlie, and heartily vſe it: And firmely belieue that which <hi>Dauid</hi> the Prophet for our good incouragement hath written in <hi>Pſ.</hi> 145.19. <hi>God is nere to thoſe which cal vpon him, &amp; will fulfill the deſire of them that feare him. and deliuer the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  </hi> Whenſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer therefore we are tempted, allured, and drawne on by <hi>Sathan</hi> through coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſſe to riches, through ambition to honour, through enuy to murther, through co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cupiſence to adultery, through intemperance to gluttony; or to be ſhort through any other ſinne to iniquity. Let vs ſtraight waies by prayer craue for power and ſtrength from aboue, to ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come theſe temptations, and eſpecially the moſt dangerous ſuggeſtion of Deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>payre.</p>
               <p>This kind of Armour is alwaies ready at hand, ſo that <hi>Satan</hi> can no ſooner at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt any thing againſt vs, but this wea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pon
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:2663:26"/> is as ſoone ready (if we heartily and zealouſly lay hold thereon) to repell and vanquiſh al his practiſes againſt vs: And therefore, <hi>Pray, pray, pray.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 2.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>The ſecond Chapter concerning reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies and helps againſt ignorance, the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond cauſe of Deſperation, entreated of before in Chap. 4.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>COncerning the ſecond cauſe of Deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peration, to wit, ignorance; Our Lord <hi>Ieſus Chriſt</hi> who was nothing ignorant of the manifold miſchiefes, and of the manifeſt dangers that the Diuell leadeth ſilly men into, as it were blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>folded through blinde ignorance: and hee knowing that Ignorance is rather the mother of deſperation (as heretofore in the 4. Chap. of the cauſes of Deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration hath beene ſufficiently prooued) then of Deuotion, as the Papiſts haue in this point ignorantly taught &amp; main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taind: hath in his owne perſon, &amp; with his owne mouth exhorted and admoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed all men,<note place="margin">Io. 5.29</note> to <hi>Search the Scriptures,</hi>
                  <pb n="35" facs="tcp:2663:26"/> which is a leſſon in this caſe moſt neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary for all men, to learne thereby to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuer themſelues out of the dangerous gulfe of Ignorance, and ſo conſequently out of many other ſinnes, and finally out of deſperation; where-into thouſands through Ignorance haue bene implun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged and drowned for euer.</p>
               <p>Let vs therefore for the remedie and auoiding of finall Deſperation,<note place="margin">Remedies againſt Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance.</note> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto ſo many runne headlong through Ignorance, little knowing, and leſſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garding what they doe, vntill it be too late; receiue the word of God, which (as <hi>S. Iames</hi> ſaith) <hi>is able to ſaue our ſoules:</hi> with al readines like vnto the Nobleme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of <hi>Berea,</hi> &amp; ſearch the Scriptures daily.<note place="margin">Act. 17.11</note> Let vs ſeeke after the knowledg of God in time. And as the Prophet <hi>Eſay</hi> ſaid,<note place="margin">Eſa. 55 6.</note> 
                  <hi>Seeke the Lord whiles he may be found &amp; cal vpon him whils he is neere.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance.</note> And let vs be aſſured of this y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> al ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ner of Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance is perillous; but wilful Ignorance of all other is moſt perilous (For it is (as a learned Writer hath affirmed) a plain Prognoſtication,<note place="margin">A. D. in the plaine mans path to heauen.</note> &amp; a demonſtratiue ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument of eternall death. It is a moſt horrible and fearefull thinge for a man
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:2663:27"/> to refuſe inſtructions, diſpiſe counſaile, harden their Hearts, ſtoppe their eares, and cloſe vp their eyes againſt God this is the very vp ſhot of euerlaſting ruine.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">What the Ignorant muſt doe</note>Let the ignorant therefore that ſtand in this dangerous eſtate repayre with al diligence and attentiueneſſe vnto the learned Miniſters &amp; diſpencers of Gods moſt ſacred word, and at their mouths enquire the knowledge of Gods lawes. This doth God himſelfe commaund vs by the Prophet <hi>Malachie,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Malac 4.</note> And when we feele our conſciences wounded, let vs af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the example of the Godly, faithfull, and deuout people, who after the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of Gods word preached, came vnto <hi>Peter</hi> and the reſt of the Apoſtles, ſaying, <hi>Men &amp; brethren,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Act. 2.</note> 
                  <hi>what ſhall we do?</hi> Euen thus I ſay, let vs come vnto Gods Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters,<note place="margin">Counſell f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r the ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry.</note> and confeſſe &amp; acknowledge our great blindnes and ignorance, and ſay vnto them. Help vs, inſtruct vs, teach vs ſet vs in the way, &amp; guid vs in the paths of the knowledge of God and of our ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation:<note place="margin">What the true Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of gods word are.</note> for ſurely they are the Phiſitions and Surgions of our ſoules, ſo that if w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> repayre vnto them, they ſhall giue vs t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> drinke of the holeſome waters of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:2663:27"/> to quench our thirſt of Ignorance: they are the diſpencers of the manifolde graces of God, &amp; the Lords Stewards to giue each one of vs our portions in due time.</p>
               <p>We haue not Chriſt alwaies amongſt vs (as appertayning to his bodely pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence) but as himſelfe ſaith, we haue <hi>the Poore</hi> alwaies amongſt vs: euen ſo alſo we haue not <hi>Chriſt</hi> himſelfe (that body I meane which ſitteth at the right hand of God the father) alwaies with vs: but yet our Lord <hi>Chriſt,</hi> aſcending vp on high, gaue vnto men among other giftes, this gift alſo (if we could rightly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſider of it) of no ſmal value, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Paſtors &amp; Doctors that is, the Miniſters of the Goſpell of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> that might inſtruct, informe, and teach vs in the way of life, that might declare vnto vs the ſecret counſailes &amp; hiden miſteries of God,<note place="margin">How the true mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of Gods word are to be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted of</note> thet might arme vs with the <hi>Sword of the Spirit,</hi> which is the word of God, to encounter &amp; reſiſt our deadly enemy the Diuel ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with. Let vs ioyfully receiue them; for who ſo receiueth them as they ought to be. receiueth alſo with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, him that ſent them, whoſe Meſſengers they are, Let
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:2663:28"/> vs heare them, for they bring vnto vs the word of life: Let vs giue credit vnto the Lords Miniſters, &amp; Glory vnto the Lord himſelfe, that hath giuen in his great loue this bleſſing vnto vs, to haue his meſſengers and Ambaſſadours abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding among vs, to declare and make known vnto vs by them, what his own good will and pleaſure is in all thinges, to the auoiding of this blind ignorance, the very mother of Deſperation, and ſo conſequently of eternall Damnation with the Author thereof, and his curſed Angels for euer.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 3</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Of the great ſeruitude &amp; bondage of ſins and of the remedies thereof.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>COncerning the great ſeruitude and bondage of ſin being the third (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore noted) cauſe of Deſperation, for the helpes and remedies thereof this haue I briefly to ſay, that what though we haue bin ſeruants vnto ſinne, and haue bene preſſed, and ſurpreſſed with the bondage thereof, ſo that we muſt néedes confeſſe,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:2663:28"/> (vnleſſe we ſhould proue our ſelues ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ars, and thrt there were no truth in vs) that we through our often doing of thoſe thinges which we ſhould not haue done; &amp; on the other ſide, through our leauing off thoſe things vndon which we ſhould haue done, haue moſt iuſtly deſerued Gods threatned curſes and plagues to light on our bodies, our ſoules, our chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, our ſtockes, our croppes, &amp; euery thing elſe we goe about, &amp; put our hands vnto. What though our ſinnes fight a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt our ſoules, and gnaw our conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences, and be ready euen out of hand to lead vs into the moſt dangerous ſtate of Deſperation?<note place="margin">Examples tending to the ſtrength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of our faith hope and patience againſt deſperati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on-</note> What though wee haue contended &amp; fallen out with our brethra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>? as did <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barnabas,</hi> who were ſo hot in contententio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> one againſt another, that they forſooke one an others compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny in high diſpleaſure and heat of their ſtomacks, the one taking with him <hi>Luke</hi> the other <hi>Iohn?</hi> What though wee haue yeelded vnto, practiſed!, and followed Oppreſſion, Extortion, polling, pilling and wreſting that wee can by hooke or crooke from our brethren?<note place="margin">Luke 19 2</note> So did <hi>Za<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oheus,</hi> yet notwithſtanding after his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:2663:29"/> his forſaking &amp; ceaſing from bad getting, his reſtitution, and almes giuing, receaued that moſt chearefull and comfortable ſaying of Chiiſt, <hi>This day is ſaluation entred into thine houſe,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luk. 19 9</note> What though we haue bin théeues, rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers &amp; ſtealers of our neighbours goods? ſo was the théefe that was crucified with <hi>Chriſt;</hi> and yet vpon eis humble, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trite, and ſorrowfull confeſſion of his ſinnes, he heard this moſt ſweete word from Chriſt, <hi>This day ſhalt thou be with mee in Paradiſe.</hi> What though we haue murthered and ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d the blood, or cauſed the bloud to be ſhed of ſome of our bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren? ſo did <hi>Dauid</hi> to <hi>Vrias,</hi> and yet vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his zealous, inward &amp; true vnfained ſorrowfulnes &amp; repentance, hee was not taken away in his ſinne, but found par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don. And ſo did the Iewes which put to death the Lord of life.</p>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Manaſſes</hi> was an Idolater, he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Temple of God, hee with ſtood <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> beat downe the truth,<note place="margin">2 K<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> hee ſet vp Ido<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ry, he was a coniurer &amp; a South<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſhed aboundance of Innocent <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, ſo that the ſtreets flowed there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with, he committed more abhominati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:2663:29"/> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the <hi>Cananites</hi> or <hi>Amorites</hi> who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for their filthines the Lord cut off out of the land of the liuing, he ſacrificed his ſonnes and daughters to Diuells: and yet vpon his true returning to the Lord from the bottom of his heart, he found fauour and mercy.</p>
               <p>If our ſinnes then,<note place="margin">2. Chr. 33.</note> or the ſins of any one of vs, were as grieuous as euer were the ſins of <hi>Manaſſes,</hi> yet vpon our true and vnfained returne to the Lord ſhall we deſpayre of his mercy? ſhall we or may we, or daie we thinke that the mercy and power of the Lord is ſhorte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned? or that God is not the ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>e God he was? Is he not as ready to pardon &amp; forgiue ſinnes, the ſinnes of a m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penting, returning, &amp; faithfully c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ling vpon him, as euer he was the ſinnes of <hi>Manaſſes?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>All theſe examples, and many more, are written for our learning, comfort &amp; ſtrengthning of our faith, hope, and pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience, that we ſhould in no wiſe deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>payre vpon our true repentance, neither for the multitude nor grieuouſneſſe of our ſinnes.</p>
               <p>And likewiſe alſo it is written for the
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:2663:30"/> bruſing, &amp; as it were euen for the brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of the backe of all damnable Deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peration, and to hold the hearts, and to reſtore the fainting and dull ſpirites of all ſuch as the ſeruitude and bondage of ſinne (this our third cauſe of Deſperati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) doth vexe and preſſe downe: It is (I ſay) written, that the <hi>Sonne of man is come to ſaue mens liues.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luk. 9.56</note> And he himſelfe hath ſaid, <hi>I am come to call not the iuſt but ſinners,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Math. 10. Math. 20 Ioh. 3. Wherfore Chriſt came into this world</note> And againe, <hi>Ieſus Chriſt is come to giue his life a redemptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny.</hi> Alſo <hi>God the father hath not ſent his Son to iudge the World, but to the end the world may be ſaued by him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now what is it to ſaue &amp; not to iudge? but to deliuer from death and damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; wherein we lay in the middeſt of the bondage of ſinne; for ſinne is the death and damnation of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oule: Now hee cannot ſaue vs except ſinne bee firſt taken from vs; And therefore, and for this cauſe came <hi>Ieſus Chriſt</hi> the Son of God,<note place="margin">Ioh. 8.</note> and hee hath declared himſelfe to the world to the end that he ſhould take away ſinnes, and ſhould deſtroy the workes of the Diuell. If it bee ſo that <hi>Ieſus Chriſt</hi> be come into the world to
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:2663:30"/> take away ſins; and if the ſame were his intent and his meſſage, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> purpoſe of <hi>Ieſus Chriſt</hi> ſhall not fayle at all and his meſſage remaineth ſtedfaſt and true; he then without all doubt, hath taken away this which y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Diuell would perſwade vs to be a cauſe of Deſperation, this great ſeruitude and bondage of ſinne, from all thoſe that truſt in him, and do verily be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue, and perſwade themſelues in the bottome of their conſciences that it is moſt true: but yet how comes this to paſſe? to wit by <hi>Ieſus Chriſt</hi> onely by his owne free grace and mercy; by the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefitts and merites of himſelfe, who is our onely Sauiour, without any other meane or merit;<note place="margin">Ioh. 1.29</note> for he is the only <hi>Lamb of God which taketh away the ſins of the world.</hi> As alſo <hi>S. Peter</hi> ſaid to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Iewes,<note place="margin">Act. 4 12.</note> 
                  <hi>There is none other ſaluation, but onely in Ieſus Chriſt; for among men there is gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> none other name vnder heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by we muſt be ſaued.</hi> And ſo Chriſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe ſaid after he was riſen from y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> dead. <hi>It muſt needs haue bin,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luk. 24.44.</note> 
                  <hi>that Chriſt muſt haue ſuffered death &amp; that he muſt haue riſen the third day fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the dead, &amp; that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of life, &amp; forgiuenes of ſins muſt
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:2663:31"/> be preached in his name to all people &amp; to all nations,</hi> O ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſwe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>te and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable are theſe wor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s and ſayings of God which is the onely eternall truth indeed? O how worthy are they to bée laid v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in the depth of our hearts, and to haue our whole confidence repoſed freely vp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n them! And to the <hi>Colloſſians</hi> it is ſai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,<note place="margin">Colloſ. 2</note> 
                  <hi>God hath quickened vs which were dead in ſins with Ieſus Chriſt, forgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing vs all our treſpaſſes, &amp; hath put out the hand-writing that was againſt vs, he euen took it out of the way, &amp; faſtened it on the Croſſe.</hi> What meaneth he by this, but onely that <hi>Ieſus Chriſt</hi> hath taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the obligatio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of our debt? to wit, that we did owe for our ſinnes, and hath taken it &amp; tied it wi h himſelfe vpon the Croſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>; &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ath indéed paid it full bitter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o alſo is for vs, &amp; will ſurely take away this grea ſeruitude &amp; bondage of ſin (wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ch the Diuel would vſe as an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument of Deſperation againſt vs) in caſe we wil belieue his word, &amp; that we can ſetle our minds &amp; quiet our hearts, to account &amp; eſteeme his bitter paſſion and merits to bee ſo great and of ſuch value, that they are able, effectuall, and
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:2663:31"/> of ſufficient ſtrength, to obtaine theſe oforeſaid thinges for vs. And <hi>Chriſtes</hi> prayer to his heauenly Father is heard, and remaineth heard continually when he praied, ſaying,<note place="margin">Ioh. 17 20</note> 
                  <hi>I pray not for theſe alo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e</hi> (meaning his three preſent Diſciples) <hi>but for them alſo which ſhall belieue in me through their word:</hi> Wherefore the ſame prayer includeth euery one of vs, ſo farre forth as wee belieue, and place the ſame in our hearts, and wholy repoſe our ſelues thereon.</p>
               <p>And <hi>S. Peter</hi> ſaith, <hi>Ieſus Chriſt hath co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded vs to preach vnto the people,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Act. 10.42 43.</note> 
                  <hi>&amp; to teſtifie that it is he that is ordayned of God a Iudge of the quick &amp; the dead, &amp; that to him all the Prophets giue witnes, that through his name all that belieue, ſhould receiue remiſſion of ſins.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Moreouer, <hi>S. Paul</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">2. Cor. 5.21.</note> 
                  <hi>God hath made him which knew no ſinne, ſinne for vs to the end that wee ſhould be made the righteouſnes of God in him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And here is to be noted,<note place="margin">What man<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ner of righ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teouſnes God<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>qu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ireth at our hands</note> what righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes, or Iuſtice &amp; goodnes that is, which God requireth and eſteemeth; which is no other, but that onely which dwelleath and holdeth vppon the Iuſtice
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:2663:32"/> Goodneſſe, and merit of <hi>Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> being vtterly ignorant of the Iuſtice or Righteouſnes and goodnes which many do ſeeke in their owne good workes.</p>
               <p>But yet when I ſtand ſo much vpon this point, to prooue that our ſinnes ſhould be no cauſe of Deſperation, (a thing which the diuell greatly vrgeth &amp; obiecteth againſt the conſcience of an ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant man) for that our ſins are taken away by the innocent Lambe <hi>Chriſt Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus,</hi> that he hath ſufficiently paid the ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome therof, &amp; that we are become righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous, by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> righteouſnes of <hi>Ieſus Chriſt:</hi> it is not here my meaning, neither wold I haue any man ſo to miſtake mee, and miſ vnderſtand me, that I thinke, or would haue any other men to thinke hereby, that there is no more ſinne in vs or that ſinne dwelleth not in theſe our mortall bodies:<note place="margin">Sin dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>h euen in the be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>leeuers, &amp; in the moſt righteous men in the world: but yet raig<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neth not in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> for I confeſſe it plainly, and it is too true, that ſinne indeede dwelleth in vs; but yet to the great com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort of an afflicted conſcience againſt deſperation I affirme it (hauing the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſcriptures for my teachers herein) that although the roote of ſin, the naughty diſpoſition, and inclination to ſinne re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maineth
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:2663:32"/> alwaies ſtrong in a Chriſtian, and neuer can be wholy vanquiſhed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we put off by death, this ſinfull fleſh of ours; although (I ſay) it doe dwell in vs, yet it doth not raign in any Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> beleeuer; yet it is not able to damne a true faithfull beleeuer: it cannot (I ſay) damne vs for as much as we are in <hi>Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> and that we doe fight and ſtriue againſt the remanent of ſinne, albeit we ſtagger and wauer ſometimes, and doe feele and perceiue our ſelues to be aſſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led ſomtimes by the ſtrong temptations of the diuell, and the fleſh. This is it that <hi>S. Paul</hi> writeth of when he ſaith,<note place="margin">Rom. 8.1</note> 
                  <hi>There is now no damnation to them that are in Chriſt Ieſus, which walke not after the fleſh but after the ſpirit.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The remanent and roote of ſin dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth alwaies in vs, but we like vnto li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centious worldlings, giue it not the bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle, and ſuffer it not to range too farre, and to take too deepe a roote, but wee breake it, tame it, and make it ſubiect vnto vs by walking after the ſpirit. &amp;c. and then nothing more ſure then that there ſhal be no condemnation at al vnto vs thereby, neither any cauſe of deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:2663:33"/> therby, for that we are iuſtified by our faith and deliuered from ſinne; to wit, theſe ſinnes which might condemne vs, the roote, originall, and mother of ſinne yet notwithſtanding ſtill aby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, remayning and dwelling in vs; againſt which we warre and ſtriue, as long as we continue in this life; but the victory remaineth to our Chieftaine and head-Captaine <hi>Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> by the law of his ſpirit which maketh vs to liue in him, and hath ſet vs free from the right of ſin and death (in ſuch ſort that wee may no more feare ſinne, nor death) by <hi>Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> who hath ouercome all for our wealth, and hath reconciled vs eternally to his Father; who as our deare Father, from hence-forth will ſhew fauour vnto vs, for the loue of <hi>Ieſus Chriſt</hi> his deare Sonne, and ſo will take from vs all our ſinnes as though we had neuer commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted them. Euen ſo doth he promiſe, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,<note place="margin">Mich. 7.18 19.</note> 
                  <hi>God is one God willing to ſhew vs grace &amp; mercy, he wil turn to vs &amp; wil be fauourable, &amp; he wil take away our ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities, &amp; caſt our ſinns into the depth of the ſea.</hi> And again it is ſaid of Gods wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull mercies, <hi>The Lord is full of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <pb n="49" facs="tcp:2663:33"/> &amp; mercy,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 103.8.9.10. &amp;c</note> 
                  <hi>long ſuffering &amp; of great goodnes. He wil not alwaies be chiding, neither keepeth he his anger for euer He hath not delt with vs after our ſins, nor rewarded vs according to our iniquities. For look how high the heauen is in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon of the earth ſo great is his mercy alſo towards them that feare him: Looke how wide alſo the eaſt is from the weſt, ſo far hath he ſet our ſins fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs. Yea, like as a father pittieth his own children; euen ſo is the Lord merciful vnto them that feare him: for he knoweth wherof we be made; he remembreth that we are but duſt &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Of the great mercies of God towards ſinners, read more in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 145.8.9.<note place="margin">Places of holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting forth Gods great mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies.</note> and 147.8.10. &amp; in <hi>Ioel.</hi> 2.13. <hi>Math.</hi> 18.11. 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.3. <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.4. 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.13. vnto the 18. verſe.</p>
               <p>Surely theſe places are words of moſt rare and ſinguler comfort, and they be certaine, firme, ſure, and vnchangeable ſpoken and pronounced by the eternall verity it ſelfe, &amp; therefore not to be miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truſted or diſpaired of. But yet let vs take heed, leaſt that verſe be verified in vs, <hi>Stulti cum vitant vitia in contraria currunt.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:2663:34"/>
               <p>Let vs not abuſe Gods mercies, making a cloake thereof to couer our ſinnes: Let vs not preſume too far, and ſay as in <hi>Eccleſiaſtic.</hi> 5.6. <hi>The mercy of God is great, he wil forgiue my manifold ſins: for mercy &amp; wrath commeth from him &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 4</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>The fourth Chapter concerning the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medies to be vſed againſt the fourth cauſe of Deſperatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ariſing of the doubts ſuggeſted by the Diuel vnto many men to bring them into diſpayre of their ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation, by meanes of the ſmall number of thoſe that ſhall be ſaued, in compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the great nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber of the reprobate.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">A cata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue or rehearſall of many thinges whereby the Diuell craftily tempteth men to ſin and deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration.</note>GReat indeed is the power, &amp; mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold &amp; meruailous are the polices, deuices, wiles, ſubtilties, aſſaults, and ſuggeſtions, wherewith and wherby that wylie Foxe, that old bitten Dogge, that ſubtle <hi>Sathan</hi> the Diuell, dayly and hourely practiſeth to entice, allure, and euen as it were to force multitudes of men heare on earth, into one ſinne or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, wherunto he findeth and proueth
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:2663:34"/> them to be naturally inclined; and laſt of all vpon one occaſion or other, into Deſperation.</p>
               <p>If he eſpieth a man to be rich,<note place="margin">How the diuel temp<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teth by riches.</note> and to haue worldly bleſſings through the gift of God, then will he apply him earneſtly by his proſperity to lull him aſleepe in the forgetfulneſſe of God, in worldly Pleaſures, pleaſant Vanities, &amp; tranſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory delights, comforts, and ſolaces; and by truſting in his riches to lift vp him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe arrogantly aboue others; to ſwell in pride, and to contemne his brethren, committing (and that with great ſawci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and boldneſſe) manie fond, palpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and groſſe errors and follies, againſt Gods word, euen as if hee ſhould ſay, Who is the Lord?</p>
               <p>On the other ſide if a man be poore, he laboureth therby to make him contemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tible before the world,<note place="margin">How the diuel temp<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teth by po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerty.</note> to pinch and nip him with the want of many thinges ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary both for backe and belly, that hee ſeeth before his face many others haue in great &amp; in aboundant meaſure; he ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liciteth him to ſteale,<note place="margin">Pro. 30.9</note> to take the name of God in vaine, to ſeeke after gaine by vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honeſt, vnlawfull, and vngodly meanes;
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:2663:35"/> to murmure, diſtruſt, blaſpheme, and deſpayre.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">How the Diuell tempteth by friends Gen. 3.6. Iob. 2.9 Eſter 5.14</note>If a man haue friends he will vſe them as his inſtruments, to tempt vnto ſome euill by their lewd and wicked coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaile, as he did procure <hi>Euah</hi> to doe vnto <hi>Adam, Iob</hi> his wife to <hi>Iob. Haman</hi> his Wife vnto <hi>Haman.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">How the Diuell tempteth by ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies.</note>If thou haſt enemies then will he prick thee foreward by their procedings and dealings againſt thee, vnto vniuſt chol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler, wicked anger, and diueliſh reuenge.</p>
               <p>If thou be carefull for thy family, wife and children, he will take hold vpon that occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to ſtuffe thy heart with too much deſire of hauing,<note place="margin">How the Diuell tempteth by careful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes.</note> and getting by right or by wrong, and thereby through extreame couetouſnes, make thee to forgoe all godlines and piety.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">How the Diuell tempteth by ſecurity and care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſnes.</note>On the other ſide if thou be careles, that's it that he can make vſe of alſo; for as <hi>S. Bernard</hi> ſaith, <hi>Infert diabolus ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritate<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, vt inferat etiam perditionem. &amp;c.</hi> In heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Angels became diuels. In Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radiſe <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Euah</hi> fel into diſobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence. In the ſchoole of <hi>Chriſt, Iudas</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came a traitor to his Lord &amp; Maiſter: &amp; al this (ſaith <hi>S. Bern.</hi>) through ſecurity
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:2663:35"/> and retchleſnes, to keepe themſelues in that good ſtate wherein they were once ſet.</p>
               <p>Haſt thou ſtrength? thereby will hee take occaſion to embolden and harden thee to doe iniury and wrong, and to ſet vpon thy weaker.</p>
               <p>Haſt thou health and a ſtrong able bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy?<note place="margin">How the Diuell tempteth by ſtrength by health ableneſſe of body &amp; beauty.</note> by thoſe will hee induce and entice thée to one kinde or other of lewdnes and diſſolutnes.</p>
               <p>Haſt thou beauty? that will he make an inſtrument for bawdry; an inticeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t and an allurement to voluptuouſnes &amp; wanton delights.</p>
               <p>Haſt thou honour and dignity in the world?<note place="margin">How the diuel temp<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teth by ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and dignity.</note> thereby will he blow the bellows of pride, audacity, and boldneſſe, to op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe, to cruſh, and tread vnder foote thine inferiours.</p>
               <p>Haſt thou viuacity,<note place="margin">How the Diuell tempteth by quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit &amp; ſharp<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes of wit.</note> &amp; quicknes of ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, and ſharpenes of wit and learning? theſe alſo will he ſtriue to abuſe &amp; wreſt to ſerue his turne to excogitate, inuent, and deuiſe a thouſand vanities; yea, &amp; all the rare and excellent guiftes of God, which God doth beſtow on any man: this Diuell, this arch-enemy of man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:2663:36"/> will leaue no waies, nor meanes vnattempted, to procure man to abuſe the ſame to a cleane contrary ende (if it were poſſible) to that for which they were beſtowed.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">How the diuel temp<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teth by gods word</note>And finally the very Word of God, gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen through Gods great and infinite goodneſſe, to be our ſpirituall Sword, to reſiſt and encounter the Diuell with; which as <hi>S. Iames</hi> ſaith, <hi>is able to ſaue the ſouls of men:</hi> which as <hi>S. Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>is the power of God to ſaluation to euery one that beleeueth:</hi> which as holy <hi>Dau.</hi> ſaith; <hi>was a lanterne vnto his feet &amp; a light vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his paths.</hi> This, euen this, wil the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uil ſo far forth as euer he may, with al y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cunning fetches, crafts, &amp; policies that euer he can deuiſe,<note place="margin">How the Diuell will abuſe, wreſt, and miſapl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> gods word</note> ſeeke to abuſe, wreſt, and miſapply, from the true meaning ſence and ſignification thereof, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme lies, vntruths and hereſies, ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>by: he will draw ſome texts and ſenten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, thereof to bring men into preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of their owne Vertues, Worthines and merits to their vtter ouerthrow. And likewiſe with ſome other places &amp; ſentences thereof, he will beſtir himſelfe to bring men to wauer in faith, to doubt
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:2663:36"/> of Gods graces and mercies through <hi>Chriſt,</hi> &amp; ſo finally to fall into vtter deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peration. And thus doth he dayly abuſe and wreſt all thoſe places of holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures before noted and alledged in the fourth cauſe of Deſperation, tending to prooue the ſmall number of thoſe that ſhall be ſaued, in compariſon of the huge and great number of the reprobate.</p>
               <p>Thoſe places I ſay, doth he vrge vpon the conſciences of many in the world, &amp; by his miſapplying of them, and by his miſconſtruing of <hi>Chriſts</hi> purpoſe, drift, and meaning therein, draweth and dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth them to feare and to tremble to doubt and deſpayre, that they are none of that ſmall number, ſeeing ſo few ſhall be ſaued.</p>
               <p>But O thou man that art thus tried,<note place="margin">The true vſe of thoſe Scriptures which the Diuell ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſe, to bring men to deſpera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by.</note> tempted, and drawne towards tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion! for thy remedy and helpe herein <hi>Search the Scriptures,</hi> and conſider vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thoſe places, to what end and purpoſe <hi>Chriſt</hi> deliuered this doctrine, and thou ſhalt anon proue and finde, that his meaning was nothing leſſe then to driue men into diſpayre, but rather hereby to exhort, perſwade, and to giue caueats,
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:2663:37"/> and warning peeces vnto all men that run at randome after the world, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member them ſelus, and their dangers, and tickle ſtates; to awake &amp; rouſe them vp that are ſo faſt lulled a ſleepe in the dangerous cradle of ſecurity, and retch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſneſſe, that ſo they might be touched, mooued and ſtirred vp to embrace in time when time ſerues, a farre more di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligent and watchfull care of their ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that by ſuch meanes they may bee found in the number of <hi>Chriſts</hi> litle flock and of thoſe few that ſhal be ſaued; who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> exhorteth to <hi>make an end of their ſaluation with feare &amp; trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Phi. 2.1.</note> by which they might be made more carefull and more diligent in that theire ſo waighty a buſines.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 5</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>The fift Chapter wherein are contained the comforts, helpes &amp; remedies againſt the fift cauſe of deſperatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which is the heauy and great waight of croſſes, affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, troubles and neceſſities, that God ſuffereth to fall vpon many in this life.</p>
               </argument>
               <pb n="57" facs="tcp:2663:37"/>
               <p>MOſt true, moſt notable, and moſt comfortable for the diſtreſſed &amp; af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted children of God,<note place="margin">Ro. 8.22.</note> is that golden ſentence of the holy Ghoſt, penned by his choſen veſſell S <hi>Paul, Rom.</hi> 8.28. <hi>All things work together for the beſt, to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that loue God.</hi> For euen the afflictions &amp; troubles of Gods children are ſo ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied vnto them by the ſpirit,<note place="margin">He. 12.10</note> that by the ſame they are made <hi>pertakers of Gods holines.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Heb. 12.14 1 The. 1.6</note> By the ſame they enioy the qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>et frut of <hi>Righteouſneſſe.</hi> By the ſame they attaine vnto a greater meaſure of <hi>Ioy in the holy Ghoſt.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gal. 6, 14 1, Cor, 11 32,</note> By the ſame the world is cruſified to them, and they to the world. By the ſame they are made, conformable to <hi>Chriſts</hi> death, By the ſame they are kept from the condemna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the wourld.<note place="margin">Rom, 5, 5,</note> By the ſame they learne experience, patience, hope &amp;c.<note place="margin">The com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts and commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of the croſſes and afflictions to Gods children.</note>
               </p>
               <p>So that theſe things rightly pondred weighed, and conſidered, their Croſſes are mercies, their loſſes gaines, ther af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions are their ſchoolings, and their aduerſity their learned Vniuerſity. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoide thou <hi>Sathan,</hi> thou canſt not make theſe afflicto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, croſſes and trubles nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther good nor likely cauſes of Deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration,
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:2663:38"/> ſo they be taken, borne and vſed as they ought to bee, for it is written for the learning, comfort, helpe, and remedie of all Gods afflicted children, whome thou wouldeſt full gladly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade, that their afflictions are ſignes &amp; prognoſticating tokens of Gods wrath; and ſo conſequently if thou couldſt, thou wouldſt draw them therby to deſpaire of Gods loue &amp; mercy.<note place="margin">Pro. 2.12.</note> It is written I ſay; <hi>That the Lord correcteth him whom he loueth, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as the father doth the child in whom he delighteth.</hi> And againe, <hi>My ſon,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">He. 12.5 6 7.8.9. &amp;c.</note> 
                  <hi>deſpiſe not the chaſtning of the Lord neither faint when thou art rebuked of him, for whom the Lord loueth he chaſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth; &amp; he ſcourgeth euery ſon that he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiueth. If ye indure chaſtning, God offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth himſelfe vnto you, as vnto ſons; for what ſon is it who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the father chaſteneth not? If therfore ye be without correction, whereof al are pertakers, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> are ye baſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards &amp; not ſons,</hi> &amp; ſo forth vnto the 12 .v. Theſe &amp; many other ſuch like ſayinges &amp; ſentences of the holy ſcriptures, are moſt euide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t teſtimonies, that afflictions, trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, croſſes, and vexations, are ſure to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kens of Gods grace, mercy, and fauour,
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:2663:38"/> wherby God aſſureth vs of his merciful will and fatherly good heart towards vs and not ſignes of his wrath &amp; heauy diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure, as the diuell would perſwade vs, thereby to cauſe vs to diſpaire.</p>
               <p>God indeed oftentimes ſendeth euilles euen vpon his owne beloued children;<note place="margin">Why God ſendeth e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uils to his children &amp; how he ſendeth comforts in the mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uils.</note> but yet to the intent to doe them good thereby: and withall in the middeſt of thoſe euils which he toucheth them with hee ſendeh them ſome comforts to hold their hearts with. Examples hereof you may ſee in <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Euah,</hi> for whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for their diſobedience God would baniſh them out of that moſt pleaſant place in all the world, wherein at the firſt he had placed them, yet in the middeſt of that puniſhment which he had laid vppon them, his fatherly kindneſſe ſhewed it ſelfe; for before he droue them out, hee made them coates to arme them againſt all weather, and he comforted them with a promiſe of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
                  <hi>bleſſed ſeed (Ieſus Chriſt)</hi> which ſhould reſtore that ſaluation to mankind which they had loſt by yéelding to the Serpents entiſings.<note place="margin">Gen. 3.12</note>
               </p>
               <p>This was, and this is, the moſt kind &amp; louing dealing of God with man, he wil
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:2663:39"/> make vs to ſmart a little for our ſinnes: here is his iuſtice; but yet ſo that he will not vtterly forſake vs, nor giue vs ouer for euer: here is his mercy. Auoid ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Sathan,</hi> once I ſay againe auoide; ceaſe to ſuggeſt or to ingeſt into any mans heart that he ſhould think becauſe that God doth croſſe &amp; afflict him, that therefore he doth hate, forſake, and vtter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly caſteth of thoſe with whom he ſo dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth: for this is moſt true, that as <hi>Chriſt Ieſus</hi> hath taught vs to call vpon him by the name of a <hi>Father,</hi> ſaying, <hi>Our father which art in heauen &amp;.</hi> ſo he loues vs as a Father, for his ſake: and againe hee will be more mindfull of vs, then our owne Mothers; for why? himſelfe hath ſo taught vs, and ſo promiſed, as appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth in <hi>Eſa.</hi> 49.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">How God loueth and dealeth with his children.</note>Examine and conſider but a little the procéedings and dealings of Mothers and Fathers with their children, &amp; ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by ſhall you ſee and perceiue more clearely, how God handles his children vnder their afflictions, troubles, and croſſes.</p>
               <p>It is the faſhion &amp; manner of a good kind and naturall Father, that faine
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:2663:39"/> would ſee good proofe of his child, firſt to inſtruct and teach him in the vertuous courſe and waies of wel-doing: Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to giue him oftentimes warning and monition, to keepe him in that good way which he hath taught him: Thirdly if words will not ſerue, then to ierke him now and then with the rodde: Fourthly, in caſe his child being now growne vp, waxe ſtubborne, malapart, and diſobedient, if he will needes ſpend his thrift wantonly, prodigally and ryo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſly in ill company, then comes his Father &amp; drawes him out by the eares and with a whip or cudgell, beates him till his bones cracke.</p>
               <p>All this he doth, &amp; yet with a fatherly loue, and a naturall kind affection, to feare him, and to tame him; and as it were with violence, to bring him to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendment not minding to forſake him, nor vtterly to caſt him off for euer.</p>
               <p>Euen ſuch as this is the dealing of our heauenly Father, with his vntowardly, ſtubborne, and diſobedient children: For, firſt he teacheth and inſtructeth them by the Miniſters, Teachers, and Preachers of his holy word and will:
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:2663:40"/> he giueth them often monitions &amp; war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to walke in his waies,<note place="margin">Gods rods of what ſort they are.</note> and to liue in his obedience; which if they deſpiſe and will not follow, then he vſeth his rods, as pouerty, ſicknes, diſeaſes, croſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes in their children, in their ſtocke, in their crop, and ſuch like: and when this will not ſerue, nor doe any good, but ſtil on they waxe obſtinate and ſtubborne, and care not neither for words nor war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, for ſtripes nor gentle correction; then God ſendeth vpon them more hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uy &amp; grieuous puniſhments, as plagues, peſtile<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces, dearth, caſualties of fire, wars loſſe of victory, fire and ſword, captiuity, and other ſuch like great &amp; almoſt intol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerable miſchiefs: and all theſe to worke in them acknowledging of God, hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bling the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues vnder the mighty hand of God ſorrowfulnes of hart for their negligence in ſeruing of God,<note place="margin">What God ſeeketh to worke by dealing hardly with his children.</note> and true vnfained re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, and turning againe vnto God, who then is as ready to receiue them as euer he was before, and with mercy and louing kind benefites to bleſſe them: Examples hereof holy ſcriptures afforde vs not a few, but eſpecially in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Gods choſen people the <hi>Iſralites,</hi>
                  <pb n="63" facs="tcp:2663:40"/> wherein it doth plainly appeare, that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though God did oftentimes puniſh the diſobedience &amp; falling away of thoſe his people; yet it euer prooued nothing els, but the diſpleaſure of a kinde and louing father, which ſought not their vtter o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerthrow, but rather their reformation and amendment. Let vs therefore in the like caſes, not deſpayre of Gods mercy, but amend our former wicked courſe of life &amp; yeeld our ſelues patiently vnto our heauenly father, &amp; reioyce in him, in the middeſt of our troubles &amp; afflictions, for as much as there is nothing more ſure the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that if we returne to him, but he wil likewiſe turn again vnto vs with a gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious &amp; fatherly mind, heart, &amp; good will.</p>
               <p>In this behalfe alſo is God compared and likened vnto a kind louing mother;<note place="margin">Gods af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection to his Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren like vnto a kind lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</note> for like as a natural mother is very care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, watchfull &amp; diligent about her child, ſhe trimmeth it, ſhe dreſſeth it, feedeth it, nouriſheth it, praieth to God heartily for it and doth all the good ſhe can for it with a moſt louing, tender, &amp; motherly affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; &amp; yet now and then ſhe is ſo diſqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eted in hir mind, ſo mooued and prouo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked by her childs peltiſhnes, frowardnes
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:2663:41"/> and vnrulines, that ſhe is euen againſt her owne nature, forced to bee angrye with it to chide it, and ſometimes to beat it: Euen ſo like vnto this motherly dealing, is the properly and naturall af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of God towards Mankind, who as he would not the death of a ſinner, ſo neither delighteth he in any manner of griefe, ſorrow trouble or miſfortune of man, were he not ſometimes ſtirred vp, moued, and prouoked, through our fro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardnes, vnthankfulnes &amp; vnkindnes, to chaſten &amp; correct vs, and like as a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther though ſhe bee angry and offended with her c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ild for a time, yet her diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure ſoone paſſeth away ſhe giueth it not ouer, ſhe forſaketh it not, ſhe forgetteth it not for euer. Euen after the like faſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on doth God our heauenly father deale with man: nay more mindful, more kind and more pittifull is God towards vs<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> This is moſt true, the mouth of God himſelfe hath ſpoken it; for thoſe are hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> words. <hi>Can a woman forget her own<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> child &amp; not haue compaſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> on the ſon o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> her womb?<note place="margin">Eſa. 49.15</note> though ſhe ſhould forget, yet will not I forget thee.</hi> And finally (to draw to an end of this co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pariſon) eue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="65" facs="tcp:2663:41"/> as a Mother when her child is impiſh, peeuiſh, and wayward, menaceth and threateneth it to throw it away to a Beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, &amp; ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>arreth it with ſome bugs, throſts Hobgoblins, or ſuch like, and all to make it quiet, and to cling the more vnto her: ſo likewiſe our good Father, when he ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth that we forget him make ſmaller re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>koning of him then becomes vs, &amp; waxe vnthankfull &amp; vntowardly to al goodnes declining and haſting on apace to follow all ſin and iniquity; then he ſometimes ſheweth vs t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e terrible faces of feare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full troubles and dangers, and he will bring vs into great perrils: yea, and for our vnthankfulnes, and other ſuch like offences, he will now &amp; then take away by one meanes or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ther, our health, our wealth, our peace, our liberty, our ſafety, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>And all this doth hee to cauſe vs to turne backe againe vnto him, to cleaue and cling the faſter vnto him, to pray &amp; call vpon him the more faithfully, hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tely and zealouſly for his help &amp; deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, to eſteem better of his gifts, when we enioy them, and to be more thanke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full for them when we haue them.</p>
               <pb n="66" facs="tcp:2663:42"/>
               <p>So that the very cauſes of all trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, croſſes, and calamities are not to worke in vs murmuring &amp; grudging, &amp; deſpayre, but if we wil weigh them &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider them throughly, to make good vſe of them, they may turne to our great profit and benefit, and not to our hurt: For like as a naturall Father &amp; mother doe, ſo doth God loue vs when he ſmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth vs; he fauoureth vs, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he ſeemeth to be moſt againſt vs; when hee ſeemeth to be moſt angry, hee aimeth moſt at our good, for as <hi>S. Auguſt.</hi> ſaith, <hi>Melius nouit medicus quid expediat quam aegrotus,</hi> The ſicke man the patient, neuer know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth ſo well what is good for him as doth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Phiſition.<note place="margin">God dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth with his ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>l<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren as Phiſitions and Surgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons doe with their Patients.</note> And therfore the Phyſitions &amp; Surgions whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they ſée no other reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> recouery, curing, &amp; amending of their ſick, corrupted, &amp; infected patients, vſe to miniſter vnto them tart, bitter, harſh, and vnpleaſant things, &amp; to feare, burne, and cut away corrupted, rotten, &amp; dead fleſh with ſawes, yron, and other ſuch like inſtruments, and all to ſaue &amp; cheriſh the ſound and whole parts, <hi>Ne par<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſincera trahatur,</hi> leaſt that which is whole, ſhould by the other be corrupted,
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:2663:42"/> infected and poyſoned; euen ſo doth God ſometimes (when he ſees tis beſt for vs) plague our bodies ſharply and grieuouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that our ſoule may be preferued and ſaued. The Phiſition in compounding of his beſt Triacle, vſeth Serpents, Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders and other poyſoned thinges, that w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the ſame he may driue out one poyſon w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> an other:<note place="margin">How God vſeth ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times the ſeruice of Diuells &amp; wicked men.</note> Euen ſo God (as by Hiſtories plentifully in Gods Booke it appeares) vſeth the miniſtery helpe, and ſeruice of Diuels, and of moſt diueliſh &amp; wicked men, by them to afflict and chaſtice vs, and yet to doe vs good withall; &amp; after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards burneth the roddes when he hath corrected and beaten his children with them a while. It is not giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to euery ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (I muſt needes confeſſe) to vnderſtand this, and to make this good vſe of af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions, croſſes, and troubles laid vpon them for their ſins ſake; for then ſhould <hi>Pharaoh</hi> and many of his wicked cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiers like himſelfe; then ſhould <hi>Cain,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed are not bettered by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>heir troubles &amp; afflictions.</note> 
                  <hi>Saul Iudas Iſcariot,</hi> &amp; many other vile, leaud, and deſperate perſons beſide, in their manifold croſſes, troubles, and aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſities, haue turned vnto the Lord and beene ſaued.</p>
               <pb n="68" facs="tcp:2663:43"/>
               <p>But we muſt learne and know, that ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſities,<note place="margin">Whence it commeth that afflic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and croſſes profit Gods chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren.</note> troubles, &amp; afflictions, of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues and of their owne proper nature, cannot worke and bring ſuch profits, &amp; ſo much good vnto men: But it is the ſpirit of God, which reſting in Gods faithfull children, purgeth, reformeth, comforteth, and ſtrengtheneth them, &amp; by theſe outward meanes worketh all theſe good thinges in vs: And ſo whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer goodnes hath bene ſpoken of here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore to befall men by meanes of aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſities, croſſes, and troubles, is to be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood onely of the faithfull and god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, which are taught and led by the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of God, to conſider rightly of them, &amp; to make ſuch vſe of them, that accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding as in the beginning of this Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter it is truely ſaid, to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                  <hi>that loue God all thinges worke togither for the beſt.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 8.28</note>
               </p>
               <p>Whereas on the other ſide, in the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faithfull,<note place="margin">The con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceites and opinions of the wicked in thie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> aduer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſities and toubles.</note> vnrepentant, and wicked ones, they worke after another faſhion, &amp; are of cleane contrary operation, whiles that they aſcribe their aduerſities and troubles, either to blind Fortune and Chance; as though Fortune had a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine power to worke, without the
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:2663:43"/> working and prouidence of God; or els, vnto them that are not of their own ſect, faith, and religion, as did wicked <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hab</hi> to godly <hi>Elias,</hi> or to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Magiſtrates,<note place="margin">4. Kin. 18</note> or to the Miniſters of Gods word, or to Faith and religion it ſelfe, or to the Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nets, Starres, &amp; influences of the Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; yea, and ſome wil I blame God himſelfe, as though they themſelues were ſo innocent and blameleſſe, that God deales not well with them to lay vpon them ſuch croſſes &amp; puniſhments: and ſo very buſie they make themſelues, to ſhift off all blame euer to others faults.</p>
               <p>And although their ſinnes be multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied to exceeding multitudes of offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, yet they will not ſée nor confeſſe any ſuch thinges in themſelues, nor any thing conſider, nor regard the puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of God laied vpon them, and cleauing vnto them for the ſame. But through their hardneſſe of heart, and want of faith (which is the mother of all blaſphemy, and abhomination) they can not ſpy whoſe hand it is that is againſt them, nor wherefore; or els beeing euen as it were violently forced to know it,
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:2663:44"/> that it is, the working of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord againſt them, and his vengeance in heauy diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure vpon them; yet they will not be mooued thereby, nor any thing at all ſtirred vp to amend their liues, but like vnto King <hi>Pharaoh</hi> the more God cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recteth them, the more obſtinate they ſwarue, decline, and flie away, from him being like vnto graceleſſe children, with whom neither words, threatninges, nor beating, can preuaile. Like vnto them y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> will neither daunce with the piper, nor lament with the mourner:<note place="margin">Mat. 11.17 Luk. 7.31.32.</note> and ſo farre off are they from being recouered, won, and reformed by meanes of any croſſes, afflictions, and troubles lighting on the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>; an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> following them euer as the ſhadow doth the body; that they will ſooner burſt out into al maner of impatientnes bitternes, and ſpightfull poyſonful ray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling and blaſpheming words againſt the righteouſnes of God, ſaying, That their puniſhment is greater then their ſinnes, and heauier then they can brooke or beare: and that they are wronged, and are not indifferently dealt with, &amp; ſo at the length after heaping one ſinne in the necke of an other, the Diuel brings them
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:2663:44"/> on,<note place="margin">The ends that the di<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uell brings the wicked vnto by their afflic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, and croſſss.</note> and by little and little winds them into that he gapes for, namely into a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probate mind, and deadly Deſperation, in ſo much that at the laſt they fall too, and yeelde to murthering, hanging, drowning, o by other ſuch meanes moſt miſerably, to diſpatch themſelues with their own hands, like vnto <hi>Saul, Achito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phel &amp; Iudas,</hi> ſo giuing the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mſelues ouer to the Diuell; and as they liued for a while moſt wretchedly, ſo they depart out of the world as diueliſhly, forgeting vtterly, and al-together inconſiderate, retchleſſe, &amp; carleſſe what ſhall become of them afterwards for euer. By whoſe liues,<note place="margin">Two com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities to be rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped by the liues and manner of the deaths of the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked.</note> and manner of deaths the children of God may yet reap two commodities: firſt, they ſhal be eaſed of the great trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, diſturbance, and diſcommodities, &amp; of the leaud and euill examples which they gaue to others whiles they liued. And ſecondly, they which remaine a liue after them, may learn and take warning by their ſhamfull falls, and by their ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible examples, &amp; deſperate deaths, lay hould on repentance and amendment of their liues before it be too late.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <pb n="72" facs="tcp:2663:45"/>
               <head>CHAP. 6.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>The Sixt Chapter concerning the reme<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dies againſt Deſperation, ariſing and growing by long cuſtome of ſin, &amp; by delaying &amp; putting off the forſaking of ſinne from day to day.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The great danger of cuſtome of ſinn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, &amp; of delaying of amend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of life.</note>IT is written, that the continuall and long cu to<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e of ſinne, and the delay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and putting off from time to time of the amendment of life, is one of the greateſt and moſt dangerous deceites &amp; cunning ſtratagems and pollicies which the enemy of mankind doth vſe towards the children of <hi>Adam:</hi> for hee is not ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant how that like as links in a chaine one catcheth hold and hangeth by ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and one draweth another: Euen ſo by continuance, long cuſtome, and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure ſleeping in ſinne, one ſinne draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth on another, and ſo euery day ſinne is added to ſinne, ſo that by toleration and procraſtination, ſin ſo mightily increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth, and by this meanes waxeth ſo headſtrong, that in the end, the ſaying of the Poet proueth very true; to wit,</p>
               <pb n="73" facs="tcp:2663:45"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Qui non eſt hod<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">A compa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>riſon ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wing the d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nger f <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ong <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome and w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ltring in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>inns.</note> 
                  <hi>cras minus aptus erit</hi> He that is not ready to day (to forgoe &amp; forſake ſinne) to morrow-day ſhall he be more vnfit. The Diuell knoweth wel e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough, how that like as old feſtred and long growne ſores and diſeaſes of the body are farre more dangerous, more troubleſome, and harder to be healed, &amp; require a longer time by much to be cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, then if they had beene looked to at the firſt: Euen ſo the diſeaſes of the ſoule as ſwearing, theeuing, whoring, drunk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enneſſe, &amp; ſuch like, being once long ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſtomed, ſetled, and hauing gotten an habit, are either neuer, or ſeldome, and that with greater difficulty afterwardes rooted out, then at the firſt beginning they might haue bene.</p>
               <p>And ſo by theſe diſeaſes of the ſoule, the habit thereof hauing once taken root in man, and the Diuell by them hauing gotten the ſurer hold and poſſeſſion, he endeauoureth and moſt diligently by all w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ies and meanes applieth to keep men ſtill on in vre, and practiſe w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>th old and long accuſtomed ſinnes, vntill at the length in extreamity of ſicknes towards the hower of death (if not before) he may
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:2663:46"/> by ſuch cauſes and occaſions plant and worke in the heart of man deep deſpaire to his vtter confuſion for euer.</p>
               <p>To reſiſt therefore, to remedy and helpe this canker-like creeping &amp; infecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous euill, let vs to day while it is yet to day, ſtudy to turn againe vnto God, caſt out the Diuell, and with him this great cauſe and occaſion of deſperation, euen long cuſtome of ſinne, and delay of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendment of our liues, the thing that ſo hangeth on, and preſſeth vs downe, &amp; let vs in time while we haue time take a better courſe, looking vp vnto <hi>Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> and ſet him before the eyes of our fayth, as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> onely marke to ſhoote at. And for as much as we can not turne again to the Lord, &amp; forſake our former wallow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in our former long accuſtomed ſins, except the Lord our God reach vs his helping hand to turne vs vnto him; and that repentance is not in our own power to take it vp &amp; lay it downe at our owne pleaſure,<note place="margin">Whence re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pentance &amp; amend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of life are to be had, &amp; how they are to be come by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> and that of our ſelues wée can not put it into our hearts when we liſt, exceept it firſt come from aboue; for that it is an excellent and a rare gift of God: Let vs earneſtly and heartily with our
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:2663:46"/> humble &amp; feruent praiers beg the ſame at Gods hands: Let vs practiſe much &amp; often hearing, reading, &amp; meditating the word of God and with care vſe all ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary meanes for the better, and ſpeedy attaining of it, for it is not ſo eaſie a mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to come by, as the world thinketh it: It is not an howers worke when we lie on our death-beds that will ſerue the turne: It is not,<note place="margin">Many are &amp; may be deceaued in the ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner &amp; time of their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance.</note> Cry God mercy a little for faſhion ſake, that will doe it: It is not a courſing or mumbling vp of a few prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers at a mans laſt farewel, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wil auaile: And yet if we were ſure that that would ſerue, yet we are very vn-ſure, whether we ſhall haue time, leaſure, and remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance at our laſt gaſpe, to do that yea or no: to truſt to doe it at our laſt houre, is but a broken ſtaffe to be truſted vnto, And yet it is not ſo vncertaine, but on the other ſide it is as certaine, that then we ſhall haue many byaſſes,<note place="margin">Note this you that deferre re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance vntill your laſt end.</note> many rubs and ſtoppes, many impediments to lie in our waies, and to hinder our courſe in going foreward at that time with laſt gaſping repentance, which many fond and fooliſh men relye ſo much vppon, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſt ſo much vnto, paſſing away
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:2663:47"/> their dayes, &amp; careleſly neglecting good opportunity when time ſerueth, like vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thoſe fiue fooliſh Virgins that made no preparation aforehand to be in a rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dines to enter in with the Bridegroom, till it was too late: this is I ſay, a very broken ſtaffe to truſt vnto, &amp; a thing ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry doubtfull, and vncertaine to depend vpon, or to make any reconing of, for a man to repent and cry God mercy, and make himſelfe fit and ready for God at his laſt houre, becauſe that very many in all ages and in all places haue been and are taken away oftentimes with a ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daine death, &amp; haue neither that houres nor halfe houres leaſure that they before ſpake of, and truſted ſo much vnto.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Lu. 17.27. examples ſhewing that it is dangerous truſting to the laſt hower. Gen. 19.23-</note>When the World was <hi>eating &amp; drin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, planting and building:</hi> when they were moſt ſecure and careleſſe, then ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly came the flood, and ouerwhelmed them al. Though it were a faire morning at <hi>Lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s</hi> going out of <hi>Sodome,</hi> yet by and by when they leaſt thought of any ſuch matter, they were all ſuddainly deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. When <hi>Nabuchadnezzar</hi> was moſt brag and thought himſelfe moſt ſafe and ſure,<note place="margin">Dan. 4.12.</note> ſuddenly (neuer dreaming nor once
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:2663:47"/> ſuſpecting any ſuch things) was he pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led on his knées. The Rich man thought himſelfe neuer more like to haue liued,<note place="margin">Luk. 12.20 Acts 5 are two nota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daine and vnproui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded death in Anania<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> and his wife.</note> then when he ſo buſily made ſuch great prouiſion, and laid vp ſtore for many yeares: yet was his ſoule ſodainly taken from him the very ſame night. And what knoweſt thou O man! that truſteſt ſo much, and putteſt off till the laſt day &amp; houre, whether that day and houre may not come as ſuddainely on thee, and as vnlooked for, as it did on any of theſe?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Auguſtine</hi> and <hi>Ambroſe</hi> did write one of them to the other, what his opinion was, concerning the ſtate of an old A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulterer which in their time, as hee was going in the night time to his Whore, paſſing ouer a Bridge in his way, fell in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Riuer; and ſo being drowned, was taken away ſuddainely in the very pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe of his wickedneſſe, hauing nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>their houre, halfe houre, nor minute, to cry God mercy, to repent, and to pray in.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ioannes Riuius,</hi> a learned writer,<note place="margin">Lib. 1. de ſtultitia mortaſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>um in procra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinanda.</note> &amp; of good credit, affirmed that in his time, &amp; in a village of his country, two old men lying with their Whores whom they
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:2663:48"/> had aforetime haunted,<note place="margin">Correctio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne vitae.</note> in one and the ſelfe ſame night dyed, ſodainly taken as it were with the manner: hauing like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe neither houre nor halfe houre to prepare themſelues in: for the one was ſodainely ſtabbed to death, the other was taken with a ſodaine Apoplexie, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of he preſently gaue vp the Ghoſt.</p>
               <p>And what knoweth any of vs all, or what greater priuilege hath any of vs all but that we may be ſodainely yreuented &amp; caried away in the middeſt of our ſins as theſe were? And whether we haue not the like examples of ſuch haſtye deaths heere in England, whereby many of vs haue bin diſappointed of theſe two or three houres at their laſt end, to make vs ready in, I report mee to the deaths of <hi>Earle Godwin, &amp; Grimwood of Hitch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Earle God<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>win his ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daine and fearefull death.</note> wherof the Earle after he had tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terouſly ſlaine the brother of King <hi>Ed.</hi> the third, being charged afterwards by the King therwith at <hi>Windſor</hi> (where he happened to ſit at table with the King) he falſly denied the fact, and for his better excuſe, he falſly forſwore it; and beſides all this, hee moreouer tooke a piece of bread and put it into his mouth, wiſhed
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:2663:48"/> that hee might be choaked thereof, if hée were guilty of his blood, and it fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed indeed according to his deſire: for hee being choaked therewith, yéelded vp his Ghoſt, and fell down dead in the preſence and ſight of all at the Table, &amp; from thence was had to <hi>Wincheſter</hi> to be buried.<note place="margin">Grim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wood, his ſodain and fearfull death.</note> And likewiſe the ſaid <hi>Grim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wood</hi> of <hi>Hitcham</hi> in the County of <hi>Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>folke,</hi> knowne to be a wilfull furſworne man, in the harueſt time next after his periury, feeling of no pain, complayning of no diſeaſe, being ſtrong and able to la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, as he was ſtacking vp corn, ſodain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly his bowels fel out of his body, wherof immediatly he died moſt miſerably.</p>
               <p>But what need I to ſtand beſtowing time, paper, and inke, troubling both my ſelfe &amp; future Readers, in ſetting downe the manner of the ſodain deaths of many men, ſeeing that both holy and prophane writers, &amp; dayly experience it ſelfe, may fully fraught, ſtore, and furniſh vs with infinite examples of this ſort? And what charter, priuiledge, or certain hold of life hath any of vs all, more then theſe heere before recited, or thouſands of others in the like caſe haue had?</p>
               <pb n="80" facs="tcp:2663:49"/>
               <p>O let vs not preſume therefore to run on headlong in the long and hardened cuſtome of our ſinnes! not to delay and put off the reforming of our wicked liues vntil the laſt houre: And although we be not ſtricken with ſuddain death, but haue both certaine dayes and houres before our death, yet (as I before ſaid) full ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny are the ſtops, lets, and impediments which both may, and alſo dayly doe fall out to hinder and put by this late repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance;<note place="margin">A cata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue of lets &amp; im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>diments which of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentimes fall out when wee come to the laſt houre, that hinder and put by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t l te rep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, wh ch ſo ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y truſt vnto.</note> that ſo many will needs truſt vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, and make all their reckoning of, put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of from day to day, and from yeare to yeare, till this laſt time approach and fall on them indeed: For ſo long as the extreamities of ſicknes do nip and pinch our mortall bodies, the dolours, pangs, &amp; pains racking &amp; tormenting our fleſh, will keepe our mindes ſo occupied, ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time calling on the Phiſition for helpe, ſometime turning, toſſing, and ſeeking for eaſe in euery corner of the bed; yea, &amp; from bed to bed, while ſtrength doth ſerue ſometimes taking this receipt, and ſometimes that, as the Phiſitions ſhall miniſter: ſomet<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mes turmoyled and oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupied both in minde and body by the
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:2663:49"/> working and purging of the Apotheca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries drugs receiued, ſometimes diſquiet and brawling with thoſe that are atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding about vs, crying out on them, as though their vſing and handling of vs weare the occaſion of our greater pangs and paines: with theſe and ſuch like cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances, are both bodies and minds exerciſed and vexed, ſo long as the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gour and ſtrength of fleſh and blood are able to indure and hold out, and ſo buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed here-with continually, that wee ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome haue any reſt or leaſure to frame our ſelues to any quiet calling on God; to any repentance, or vnfaigned and ze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous, crying for mercy: for if we ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times endeauour our ſelues to begin to go about it, yet behold one thing or other ſoone ſtriketh all out of minde, &amp; diſturbs vs ſo, that neuer a whit the better: but if after the powers &amp; ſences of our bodies be once worn and weakned, and the fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of the extreame dolours and panges of the ſicknes be mittigated, whereby the body after a time of wreſtling and wearying of it ſelfe, is now ſome-what quieted, and ſo the mind more ſetled, w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> then begin againe to take better hold,
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:2663:50"/> yet ſtill on either the care of children &amp; wife for want of ſufficient prouiſion for them, or griefe to depart from them, or the remembrance of lands, goods, houſes &amp; poſſeſſions, &amp; other worldly treaſures: the loue, liking &amp; delights whereof haue poſſeſſed our hearts all our life time be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, will now ſo afreſh enter &amp; trouble our heads &amp; minds, that yet time ſerues not for to continue any ſuch godly and chriſtian exerciſes as wee in health-time when wee ſhould haue done it, made no accompt of, and deferred vntill the laſt houre.<note place="margin">The effect of choller in time of extreame ſicknes.</note> Sometimes are we troubled and diſeaſed with melancholly and frenzies, choller ſhooting vp into our braines, &amp; with ſuch crampes &amp; convulſions cauſed by much euacuation, &amp; ſuch abundance of choller in our veines, that hereof, fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes the naturall effects, rauings, blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemings, vnſenſible talking, wrything of the lips, ſtrange and vn-accuſtomed wreſting and turning of the neck, buck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of the ioynts and whole body; yea &amp; often-times ſuch extraordinary ſtrength that three or foure men cannot hold vs nor rule vs without bonds. With theſe and ſuch like ſtrange effects, are many
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:2663:50"/> men depriued not onely of the right vſe of the parts of their bodies, but alſo of their reaſon and right wits, &amp; laſt of all of life it ſelfe. Are not heere then lets e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>now from the performance of that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendment of life, and crying God mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, which we put off in our life time?</p>
               <p>Put caſe that we be neither cut off with ſodaine death, nor annoyed at our laſt end with any of theſe aforeſaid lets and impediments of ſtrange diſeaſes and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary effects thereof, nor with any other ſuch like noyſome &amp; troubleſome circumſtances or ſickneſſes, but that we haue time, leaſure, and quietneſſe to doe all ſuch things as any of vs all truſted vnto at our laſt farewel with the world?<note place="margin">The diuell will bee moſt buſie to hinder repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance at our laſt houre.</note> yet will that deadly enemy, that mortall aduerſary of ours <hi>Sathan</hi> the Diuell, at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> time aboue all other, apply himſelfe; &amp; let vs looke for no other, but what vile ſinne we haue committed and delighted <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n all our life time, that wil he lay to our <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>harge, and clogge our conſciences with, &amp; to bring vs into deſperation with and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y them, he will put vs in minde, &amp; ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ifie vs with Gods ſeuere threatnings againſt ſinne. He will obiect againſt vs
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:2663:51"/> that ſaying of our Lord Chriſt,<note place="margin">Math. 19.</note> 
                  <hi>that if we would haue entred into life, we ſhould haue kept his Commandements.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Math. 7.</note> He wil tel vs that not he y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                  <hi>ſaith Lord Lord, but he that doth the wil of the father of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, ſhall enter into the Kingdome of God.</hi> He will put vs in mind that, <hi>Not the hearers of the Law, but the doers ſhal be iuſtified.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 2. Rom. 8.</note> He wil threaten vs that <hi>becauſe we haue liued according to the fleſh, we ſhall die.</hi> He wil crack vs that <hi>the vnrighteous ſhall not inherite the kingdom of God: &amp; that neither Forni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cators, nor Idolaters, nor Adulterers nor Wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tons,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Cor. 6.9.10.</note> 
                  <hi>nor Buggerers nor theeues, nor the Couetous nor Dru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kards not Railers, nor Extortioners, ſhal inherit the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And that ſuch as haue liued according to the works of the fleſh, which are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peated vp <hi>Gal.</hi> 5. ſhall not attaine to the kingdome of God.<note place="margin">1. Cor. 5. Ier. 2.</note> And that we muſt be preſented before the iudgement ſeat of Chriſt <hi>and euery man receiue particular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly according as he hath done in this life good or euill:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Apoca. 20</note> 
                  <note place="margin">2. Pet. 2.</note> 
                  <hi>euery man ſhal receiue ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his works: and that God ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red not the Angels when they ſinned:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>. 4.</note> 
                  <hi>&amp;
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:2663:51"/> if the iuſt ſhall ſcarce be ſaued, where ſhal the wicked man and ſinner appeare.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>When all theſe, &amp; a great deale more, deſcribing &amp; ſetting forth vnto vs the ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gor of Gods ſeuere iuſtice, &amp; the reckon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing wherevnto we ſhal be called, ſhal be put into our minds on our death-beds; &amp; that damned Sathan which all the daies of our liues before laboured to make vs careles &amp; negligent of the knowledge, or conſideration of any of theſe things, that ſo he might make vs the more boldly &amp; blindly to run headlong into ſinne, ſhall charge vs with this, and much more like ſtuffe, appealing to our owne con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences for witnes heereof, and ſo heer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vppon plant in our hearts déepe Deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration: Alas in what caſe ſhall our poore ſoules then ſtand? Would a man then for a thouſand worlds, and all the profits and pleaſures thereof be brought to ſuch a quandary?</p>
               <p>O thou therefore that readeſt or hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt this damnable and miſerable ſtate that ſilly ſoules may be implunged into, for the better auoyding of theſe perills, read and read againe, meditate, ponder, and put in practiſe the direction, aduice,
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:2663:52"/> and counſell in the beginning of this preſent ſixt Chapter.</p>
               <p>And take this leſſon of <hi>Ioſeph</hi> of <hi>Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mathia,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of Ioſeph of Arimathia moſt wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy to be imitated.</note> that like as hee in his life time had made a ready Sepulcre in the midſt of his Garden, which was the place of his pleaſure (as all Gardens of great men moſt commonly are) euen ſo thou in the midſt of theſe thinges wherein thou takeſt thy greateſt felicity and delight, remember yet thy graue, and what one day (thou knoweſt not how ſoone) ſhall become of thy poore ſoule, &amp; afterward of thy ſoule and body for euer.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The vſe &amp; cuſtome of he E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyptians.</note>Remember and learne likewiſe at the Egiptians, who perceiuing the mindful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of death to be a good helpe to bridle their euill actions, vſed to bring a Pic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture or Image reſembling death, into their great and ſollemne Feaſts; which fearefull and vgly ſight, trembling and ſhaking, they tooke to bee a ſpeciall occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to keepe the beholders in ſobriety, by the remembrance of their end,<note place="margin">The nota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble &amp; im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>e example of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ing Ezechi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s.</note> which they muſt all come vnto ſooner or later.</p>
               <p>And finally, learne at the good king <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zechias,</hi> when thou ſhalt be by any occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion put in remembrance of death,
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:2663:52"/> be affraid of Gods threatning, &amp; ſorrow a little before hand, leaſt thou bee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained to ſorrow, howle, and cry re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medileſſe alwayes afterwards; for ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the old ſaying,<note place="margin">Eccleſiaſt. 7.40.</note> 
                  <hi>Qui ante non cauebit poſt dolebit,</hi> he that wil not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware before ſhall afterward bee ſorrye, &amp; he that in all his doings remembreth the end, ſhal neuer lightly do amiſſe. The which wiſe remembrance of our endes, he vouchſafe to plant in our hearts, who hath full dearely bought vs, <hi>Ieſus Chriſt</hi> the righteous, to whom with his, and our heauenly father, and the holy ſpirit three perſons; and one eternall maieſty of God-head, all worthy glory, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, and praiſe, be worthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly attributed, for euer and euer <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <pb n="88" facs="tcp:2663:53"/>
               <head>CHAP. 7</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>The ſeauenth Chapter containing the Generall Preſeruatiue againſt the deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paire or doubting of Gods mercy ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing vppon any cauſe whatſoeuer.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>FOr as much as it is a thing manifeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to be proued by holy Scriptures, that a man indued with true faith it ſelfe may not withſtanding now and then be troubled and aſſaulted with motions of doubtings wauering; yea and of deſpai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring: therefore for the bridling, ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſing and ouercomming of theſe aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaults, it ſhall be good to put in practiſe theſe fiue things eſpecially.</p>
               <p>Firſt, we are to thinke and conſider thus much,<note place="margin">The firſt preſerua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpaire.</note> that as not to murther, not to ſteale, not to commit adultery, and all the reſt of the Decalogue or ten Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements, are the Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of God, and we are carefull, and ſtriue with our ſelues that we ſhould not breake any of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>; leaſt that in brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king any of them, wee ſhould ſo highly offend God, that he would therefore
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:2663:53"/> power downe vpon vs his heauy wrath and in his indignation ſeuerely puniſh vs as by many examples we ſee he hath done to others in the like offences: So alſo it is Gods commandement as well as any of the others are,<note place="margin">1 Iohn 3.23.</note> 
                  <hi>That wee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue in the name of his ſon Ieſus Chriſt:</hi> and therefore we muſt thinke we offend againſt God as grieuouſly, or rather far more grieuouſly in violating and brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king this Commandement by incredu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, doubting, wauering and deſpairing as if we ſhould ſhed mans blood, com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mit whordome, theft, periury, or any other ſuch like notorious ſinne.</p>
               <p>O what a hainous ſinne muſt it needs be to caſt no doubtes, nor diſpaire in the helpe of a mortall man in the time of neede: and yet to miſtruſt and deſpaire of the like in God? As for example, wee can ſettle our hearts to beleeue in our mortall fathers if wee ſtand in neede of meat, drinke or clothes,<note place="margin">An exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple that many men put more truſt in mortall man then in God.</note> wee then call on them, and if they promiſe vs any ſuch thinges, we can ſet our hearts at eaſe, &amp; count it as a thing done; we doubt no thing of their good will towards vs nor of the performance, of their word vnto
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:2663:54"/> vs, we depend vpon them, we relye on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly on them &amp; none other, and what they giue their word to do for vs, wee make as ſure reckoning of it, as if it were al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready in our hands.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Another example ſhewing that many men put more truſt in mortall man then in God.</note>Againe, if wee ſtand in néed of a piece of money as of x. <abbr>l</abbr> xx. <abbr>l.</abbr> xxx. <abbr>l.</abbr> or be it more or leſſe, to diſcharge ſome dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous bond, or for any ſuch like vſe by a ſet day, or to ſaue our bodies out of pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon; &amp; in the meane time, before the day appointed come, ſome one of our honeſt rich neighbors, that is counted an honeſt ſubſtantiall man, &amp; of good credit, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe vs certainely ſo much mony as we want, and ſtand in need of to ſerue our turne with, &amp; bids vs truſt vnto it that before that day hee will be ſure to helpe; we heerevpon truſt his honeſt promiſe, we beleeue his word, &amp; make as ſure ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of it as if we had it already in our purſes, and take no more thought nor care for it. O how much more ſhould we truſt Gods moſt faithfull, iuſt, and true word and promiſe; beleeue him without all diſtruſt, doubting, or diſpaire, &amp; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend vpon him who is a thouſand times more able and more willing to doe vs
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:2663:54"/> good, and to keepe touch with vs, then euer was, to euer ſhall bee any mortall earthly father or friendly neighbour?</p>
               <p>The ſecond thing in this caſe to bee conſidered of, is that euery one of vs,<note place="margin">The ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall help againſt deſperati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</note> is particularly to beleeue that hee is in the number of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that ſhall be ſaued, by the merits of Chriſts death and paſſion: for the promiſes of ſaluation in Chriſt are indefinite, excluding no particular man, as for example, <hi>God ſo loued the world,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ioh. 3.16.</note> 
                  <hi>that he gaue his only begotte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſon, to the end that all that beleeue in him ſhould not periſh but haue life euerlaſting.</hi> In w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> generall words is included euery par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular beléeuing perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, although he haue not his name ſeuerally &amp; particularly ſet down: &amp; here God excludeth none from his promiſe vnles through their vnbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leefe &amp; deſpaire they exclude their owne ſelues. If the King of <hi>Great Brittaine</hi> of his owne méere mercy &amp; motion of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion, or at the ſute and mediation of ſome Noble-man or other that is deare vnto him, ſhould freely pardon and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giue all the malefactors and priſoners of any Gaile, within his kingdoms, may we not account them very fond &amp; fooliſh
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:2663:55"/> men, and not worthy the benifit of the Kings gratious Pardon, if ſome two or three ſhould doubt and deſpaire that this generall Pardon appertaineth not vnto them, becauſe their owne particular and ſeuerall names were not therein ſpecifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and expreſſed? Euen thus is our caſe.</p>
               <p>Let not therfore any illuſion of <hi>Sathan</hi> nor feare of our owne vnworthines, nor want of our particular names, nor any other argument or reaſon whatſoeuer, withdraw vs from challe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ging our own portions and parts of Gods moſt mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull promiſes, of his free pardon, and remiſſion of our ſins: Let vs not doubt nor diſtruſt the performance and truth of Gods promiſſes.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, to comfort our ſelues, and to ſuppreſſe <hi>Satans</hi> temptations to deſpai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring,<note place="margin">The third generall helpe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peration.</note> we may further meditate and pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der with our ſelues theſe two poynts eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially: Firſt that ſéeing the Lord hath promiſed to forgiue vs our ſinnes; and to put all our wickednes out of his reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance (as by plaine and moſt manifeſt euidence of holy ſcriptures it may eaſily be proued) then it ſtandeth with his iuſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ice
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:2663:55" rendition="simple:additions"/> and truth, to performe the ſame, and that vpon ſuch a neceſſity, that hee muſt either forgiue vs our offences according to his own worde, or els we muſt count him vnfaithfull for the breach of his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes; or els, (which were horrible to thinke) iudge him an hippocrite or a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembler, if he ſhould pretend one thing, and intend another; or at the leaſt-wiſe vnconſtant in altering &amp; changing that which hee hath ſpoken with his owne mouth, &amp; ſo to be thought (which is mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrous) to be vniuſt: for the ſecond point we may conſider likewiſe to our comfort and to the weakning &amp; ouerthrow of all deſperat conceits that <hi>God hath already puniſhed Ieſu Chriſt for our offences,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eſa. 75. Whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer could be looked for at mans hands, or whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer man could bee charged with, that Chriſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed &amp; diſcharged</note> &amp; therfore cannot in iuſtice puniſh them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine in vs. We offended &amp; <hi>Chriſt</hi> was puniſhed for the ſame: Whatſoeuer in iuſtice God could either demand or man owed, that payed our Lord <hi>Chriſt.</hi> Man ought to dy, <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſatiſfied for the ſame: man ought to haue born the heauy wrath &amp; diſpleaſure of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> father; <hi>Chriſt</hi> did beare y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame: man ought to haue bin caſt down into hell, <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſatiſfied for that alſo: yea, hee ſo fully contented payed &amp; plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:2663:56"/> God the Father, for all whatſoeuer the Lord could looke for at mans hands that the father himſelfe acknowledged, and in thunder from heauen confeſſed the ſame, in the hearing of many witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes preſent; and hearing the ſame at the baptizing of our Lord <hi>Chriſt</hi> by <hi>Iohn</hi> Baptiſt in the flood Iorden: and ſo all faithfull beleeuers heereof, are heere-by fu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ly and freely acquitte and diſcharged from all debt of ſin they owed vnto God for euer.</p>
               <p>Why ſhouldſt thou then, O <hi>Sathan;</hi> ſo buſily charge vs with any ſuch matter to driue vs into deſperation, ſéeing that <hi>Sublata cauſa, tollitur etiam et effectus?</hi> The cauſe whereby thou ſo vrgeſt deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration by <hi>Ieſus Chriſt</hi> being taken away the effects alſo muſt needs then ceaſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The 4. ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall help for the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoyding of deſpai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring.</note>The fourth thing to be vſed and practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed for the better auoyding of deſpaire is that at what time ſoeuer we feele our hearts through <hi>Sathans</hi> crafty ſuggeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on aſſaulted and moleſted with this ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomous ſting of deſperation, we ſhould then ſtraight conuey our ſelues into ſome quiet and ſecret place, and there in ſome humble manner powre out our
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:2663:56"/> harts before God with inward harty &amp; zelous prayer deſiring him of his infinit mercies, to worke in our harts increaſe of faith, and to ſuppreſſe and vanquiſh all our vnbeleefe, and vtterly to expell from thence all deſpaire.</p>
               <p>The fift and laſt remedie that now I purpoſe to handle heere againſt Deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration,<note place="margin">The fift generall helpe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peration.</note> is that we frame our ſelues care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully, dilligently, and with godly zeale to vſe, and often-times to frequent ſuch godly meanes as God hath appointed and ſet forth vnto vs, for the obtaining and increaſing of faith, as (ouer and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides earneſt prayer laſt before ſpoken of) the vſe of reuerent reading, hearing, and meditating of Gods word, and the receiuing of the Sacraments, being ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Signes, and as it were Seales ſeene with our outward or bodily eyes, which inwardly doe ſignifie, and ſet forth to our hearts the ſecret and inward graces of GOD.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
